<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  
  <title><![CDATA[Moving toward what may in fact be the ultimate genocide: the destruction of the environment?!]]></title>
  <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2014-07-23T22:38:00Z</updated>
  <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Patrick M.J. Toca]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[pmjtoca@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>

  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The brink of mass extinction.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/07/23/the-brink-of-mass-extinction/"/>
	    <updated>2014-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/07/23/the-brink-of-mass-extinction/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>- 1 - This paper references a lot of sources.

- 2 - The observed facts presented here are far less frightening
than the 'denials' promoted by the 'propaganda' (media, 
governements, private and most political institutions, etc..). 
If not for our collective suicide, I wonder what is the rationale
of this 'propaganda'.

- 3 - Never, during the last 100.000 years, humanity has been
 through a variation of temperature superior to 1 degree. 
 Thence, a +6 degree variation before 2100, 
                        is beyond any 'human' experience!  
</code></pre>

<p><a id="topOfArticle"></a>
<a href="http://zcomm.org/znetarticle/the-brink-of-mass-extinction/#" target="_blank">original text</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/moebius-arzac-750.jpg" alt="Mass Extinction" title="The brink of mass-extinction." />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by Dahr Jamail, Baghdad correspondent for The NewStandard - July, 2014</h2>

<p>The Brink of Mass Extinction</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;We do not inherit the earth from our ancestors; we borrow it from our children.&rdquo;</em>
_ - Native American proverb_</p>

<p>March through June 2014 were the hottest on record <a href="#note-1">1</a> globally, according to the Japan Meteorological Agency. In May – officially the hottest May on record <a href="#note-2">2</a> globally – the average temperature of the planet was .74 degrees Celsius above the 20th century baseline, according to data <a href="#note-3">3</a> from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. The trend is clear: 2013 was the 37th consecutive year of above-average global temperatures, and since the Industrial Revolution began, the earth has been warmed by .85 degrees Celsius. Several scientific reports and climate modeling show that at current trajectories (business as usual), we will see at least a 6-degree Celsius increase by 2100.</p>

<p>In the last decade alone, record high temperatures across the United States have outnumbered record low temperatures two to one, and the trend is both continuing and escalating.</p>

<p>While a single extreme weather event is not proof of anthropogenic climate disruption (ACD), the increasing intensity and frequency of these events are. And recent months have seen many of these.</p>

<p>A record-breaking heat wave gripped India in June, as temperatures hovered at 46 degrees Celsius, sometimes reaching 48 degrees Celsius. Delhi&rsquo;s 22 million residents experienced widespread blackouts and rioting, as the heat claimed hundreds of lives <a href="#note-4">4</a>.</p>

<p>Also in June, Central Europe cooked <a href="#note-5">5</a> in unseasonably extreme heat, with Berlin experiencing temperatures over 32 degrees Celsius, which is more than 12 degrees hotter than normal.</p>

<p>At the same time, at least four people died <a href="#note-6">6</a> in Japan, and another 1,637 were hospitalized as temperatures reached nearly 38 degrees Celsius.</p>

<p>NASA is heightening its efforts to monitor ACD&rsquo;s impacts on the planet; recently, it launched the first spacecraft dedicated solely to studying atmospheric carbon dioxide <a href="#note-7">7</a>.</p>

<p>The spacecraft will have plenty to study, since earth&rsquo;s current carbon dioxide concentration is now the longest ever <a href="#note-8">8</a> in recorded history.</p>

<p><strong>Earth</strong></p>

<p>A recent report <a href="#note-9">9</a> by the National Resource Defense Council warned that summers in the future are likely to bring increased suffering, with more poison ivy and biting insects, and decreasing quality of air and water.</p>

<p>As farmers struggle to cope with increasing demands for food as the global population continues to swell, they are moving towards growing crops designed to meet these needs as well as withstand more extreme climate conditions. However, a warning <a href="#note-10">10</a> by an agricultural research group shows they may inadvertently be increasing global malnutrition by these efforts. &ldquo;When I was young, we used to feed on amaranth vegetables, guava fruits, wild berries, jackfruits and many other crops that used to grow wild in our area. But today, all these crops are not easily available because people have cleared the fields to plant high yielding crops such as kales and cabbages which I am told have inferior nutritional values,&rdquo; Denzel Niyirora, a primary school teacher in Kigali, said in the report.</p>

<p>The stunning desert landscape of Joshua Tree National Park is now in jeopardy, as Joshua trees are now beginning to die out <a href="#note-11">11</a> due to ACD.</p>

<p>Another study <a href="#note-12">12</a>, this one published in the journal Polar Biology, revealed that birds up on Alaska&rsquo;s North Slope are nesting earlier in order to keep apace with earlier snowmelt.</p>

<p>Antarctic emperor penguin colonies could decline by more than half in under 100 years, according to a recent study <a href="#note-13">13</a> - and another showed <a href="#note-14">14</a> that at least two Antarctic penguin species are losing ground in their fight for survival amidst the increasing impacts of ACD, as the Antarctic Peninsula is one of the most rapidly warming regions on earth. The scientists who authored the report warned that these penguins&rsquo; fate is only one example of this type of impact from ACD on the planet&rsquo;s species, and warned that they &ldquo;expect many more will be identified as global warming proceeds and biodiversity declines.&rdquo;</p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><strong>Water</strong></p>

<p>Given that the planetary oceans absorb approximately 90 percent of our carbon dioxide emissions, it should come as no surprise that they are in great peril.</p>

<p>This is confirmed by a recent report <a href="#note-15">15</a> that shows the world&rsquo;s oceans are on the brink of collapse, and in need of rescue within five years, if it&rsquo;s not already too late.</p>

<p>As the macro-outlook is bleak, the micro perspective sheds light on the reasons why.</p>

<p>In Cambodia, Tonle Sap Lake is one of the most productive freshwater ecosystems on earth. However, it is also in grave danger <a href="#note-16">16</a> from overfishing, the destruction of its mangrove forests, an upstream dam and dry seasons that are growing both longer and hotter due to ACD.</p>

<p>Anomalies in the planet&rsquo;s marine life continue. A 120-foot-long jellyfish is undergoing massive blooms and taking over <a href="#note-17">17</a> wider swaths of ocean as the seas warm from ACD.</p>

<p>The Pacific island group of Kiribati – home to 100,000 people – is literally disappearing <a href="#note-18">18</a> underwater, as rising sea levels swallow the land. In fact, Kiribati&rsquo;s president recently purchased <a href="#note-19">19</a> eight square miles of land 1,200 miles away on Fiji&rsquo;s second largest island, in order to have a plan B for the residents of his disappearing country.</p>

<p>Closer to home here in the United States, most of the families living on Isle de Jean Charles, Louisiana, have been forced to flee <a href="#note-20">20</a> their multi-generational home due to rising sea levels, increasingly powerful storms, and coastal erosion hurried along by oil drilling and levee projects.</p>

<p>Looking at the bigger picture, a recently released US climate report <a href="#note-21">21</a> revealed that at least half a trillion dollars of property in the country will be underwater by 2100 due to rising seas.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, the tropical region of the planet, which covers 130 countries and territories around the equator, is expanding <a href="#note-22">22</a> and heating up as ACD progresses.</p>

<p>Residential neighborhoods in Oakland, California – near the coast – are likely to be flooded<a href="#note-23">23</a> by both rising seas and increasingly intense storms, according to ecologists and local area planners.</p>

<p>On the East Coast, ocean acidification from ACD, along with lowered oxygen in estuaries, are threatening <a href="#note-24">24</a> South Carolina&rsquo;s coastal marine life and the seafood industry that depends upon it.</p>

<p>Record-setting &ldquo;100-year&rdquo; flooding events in the US Midwest are now becoming more the rule<a href="#note-25">25</a> than the exception, thanks to ACD.</p>

<p>Even Fairbanks, Alaska received <a href="#note-26">26</a> one-quarter of its total average annual rainfall in a 24-hour period earlier this summer – not long after the area had already received roughly half its average annual rainfall in just a two-week period.</p>

<p>Rising sea levels are gobbling up the coast of Virginia <a href="#note-27">27</a> so quickly now that partisan political debate over ACD is also falling by the wayside, as both Republicans and Democrats are working together to figure out what to do about the crisis.</p>

<p>Reuters released a report <a href="#note-28">28</a> showing how &ldquo;Coastal flooding along the densely populated Eastern Seaboard of the United States has surged in recent years &hellip; with the number of days a year that tidal waters reached or exceeded NOAA flood thresholds more than tripling in many places during the past four decades.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Flooding from rising seas is already having a massive impact in many other disparate areas of the world: After torrential rain and flooding killed at least a dozen people <a href="#note-29">29</a> in Bulgaria this summer, the country continues to struggle with damage from the flooding as it begins to tally the economic costs of the disasters.</p>

<p>In China, rain and flooding plunged <a href="#note-30">30</a> large areas of the Jiangxi and Hunan Provinces into emergency response mode. Hundreds of thousands were impacted.</p>

<p>The region of the globe bordering the Indian Ocean stretching from Indonesia to Kenya is now seen as being another bulls-eye target for ACD, as the impacts there are expected to triple the frequency of both drought and flooding in the coming decades, according to a recent study <a href="#note-31">31</a>.</p>

<p>Another study <a href="#note-32">32</a> revealed how dust in the wind, of which there is much more than usual, due to spreading drought, is quickening the melting of Greenland&rsquo;s embattled ice sheet, which is already losing somewhere between 200 to 450 billion tons of ice annually. The study showed that increased dust on the ice will contribute towards another 27 billion tons of ice lost.</p>

<p>Down in Antarctica, rising temperatures are causing a species of moss to thrive <a href="#note-33">33</a>, at the detriment of other marine creatures in that fragile ecosystem.</p>

<p>Up in the Arctic, the shrinking ice cap is causing drastic changes <a href="#note-34">34</a> to be made in the upcoming 10th edition of the National Geographic Atlas of the World. Geographers with the organization say it is the most striking change ever seen in the history of the publication.</p>

<p>A UK science team predicted <a href="#note-35">35</a> that this year&rsquo;s minimum sea ice extent will likely be similar to last year&rsquo;s, which is bad news for the ever-shrinking ice cap. Many scientists now predict the ice cap will begin to vanish entirely for short periods of the summer beginning next year.</p>

<p>Canada&rsquo;s recently released national climate assessment revealed <a href="#note-36">36</a> how the country is struggling with melting permafrost as ACD progresses. One example of this occurred in 2006 when the reduced ice layer of ice roads forced a diamond mine to fly in fuel rather than transport it over the melted ice roads, at an additional cost of $11.25 million.</p>

<p>Arctic birds&rsquo; breeding calendars are also being impacted. As ACD causes earlier Arctic melting each season, researchers are now warning <a href="#note-37">37</a> of long-ranging adverse impacts on the breeding success of migratory birds there.</p>

<p>In addition to the aforementioned dust causing the Greenland ice sheet to melt faster, industrial dust, pollutants and soil, blown over thousands of miles around the globe, are settling on ice sheets <a href="#note-38">38</a> from the Himalaya to the Arctic, causing them to melt faster.</p>

<p>At the same time, multi-year drought continues to take a massive toll across millions of acres across the central and western United States. It has caused millions of acres of federal rangeland to turn into dust, and has left a massive swath of land reaching from the Pacific Coast to the Rocky Mountains desolated. ACD, invasive plants and now continuously record-breaking wildfire seasons have brought ranchers to thebreaking point <a href="#note-39">39</a> across the West.</p>

<p>Drought continues to drive up food prices across the United States, and particularly prices of produce grown in California&rsquo;s Central Valley. As usual, it is the poor who suffer the most, as increasing food prices, growing unemployment and more challenging access to clean water continue to escalate their struggle <a href="#note-40">40</a> to survive.</p>

<p>California&rsquo;s drought continues to have a massive and myriad impact across the state, as a staggering one-third <a href="#note-41">41</a> of the state entered into the worst stage of drought. Even colonies of honeybees are collapsing due, in part, to there being far less natural forage<a href="#note-42">42</a> needed to make their honey.</p>

<p>The snowpack in California is dramatically diminished as well. While snowpack has historically provided one-third of the state&rsquo;s water supply, after three years of very low snowfall, battles have begun <a href="#note-43">43</a> within the state over how to share the decreasing water from what used to be a massive, frozen reservoir of water.</p>

<p>The drought in Oklahoma is raising the specter of a return to the nightmarish dust bowl conditions there in the 1930s.</p>

<p>Recently, and for the first time, the state of Arizona has warned that water shortages could hit Tucson and Phoenix as soon as five years <a href="#note-44">44</a> from now due to ongoing drought, increasing demand for water and declining water levels in Lake Mead.</p>

<p>This is a particularly bad outlook, given that the Lake Mead reservoir, the largest in the country, dropped to its lowest level <a href="#note-45">45</a> since it was filled in the 1930s. Its decline is reflective of 14 years of ongoing drought, coupled with an increasing disparity between the natural flow rate of the Colorado River that feeds it and the ever-increasing demands for its water from the cities and farms of the increasingly arid Southwest.</p>

<p>Given the now chronic water crises in both Arizona and California, the next water war between the two states looms large <a href="#note-46">46</a>. The one-two punch of ACD and overconsumption has combined to find the Colorado River, upon which both states heavily rely, in long-term decline.</p>

<p>Yet it is not just Arizona and California that are experiencing an ongoing water crisis due to ACD impacts – it is the entire southwestern United States. The naturally dry region is now experiencing dramatically extreme impacts that scientists are linking <a href="#note-47">47</a> to ACD.</p>

<p>The water crisis spawned by ACD continues to reverberate globally.</p>

<p>North Korea even recently mobilized its army <a href="#note-48">48</a> in order to protect crops as the country&rsquo;s reservoirs, streams and rivers ran dry amidst a long-term drought. The army was tasked with making sure residents did not take more than their standard allotment of water.</p>

<p>The converging crises of the ongoing global population explosion, the accompanying burgeoning middle class, and increasingly dramatic impacts caused by ACD isstraining global water supplies more than ever <a href="#note-49">49</a> before, causing governments to examine how to manage populations in a world with less and less water.</p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><strong>Air</strong></p>

<p>A recent report <a href="#note-50">50</a> provides a rather apocalyptic forecast for people living in Arizona: It predicts diminishing crop production, escalating electricity bills and thousands of people dying of extreme heat in that state alone.</p>

<p>In fact, another report <a href="#note-51">51</a> from the Natural Resources Defense Council found experts predicting that excessive heat generated from ACD will likely kill more than 150,000 Americans by the end of the century, and that is only in the 40 largest cities in the country.</p>

<p>Poor air quality – and the diseases it triggers – are some of the main reasons why public health experts in Canada now believe <a href="#note-52">52</a> that ACD is the most critical health issue facing Canadians.</p>

<p>Another recent study <a href="#note-53">53</a> shows, unequivocally, that city-dwellers around the world should expect more polluted air that lingers in their metropolis for days on end, as a result of ACD continuing to change wind and rainfall patterns across the planet.</p>

<p>As heat and humidity increase with the growing impacts of ACD, we can now expect to see life-altering results across southern US cities, as has long been predicted. However, we can expect this in our larger northern cities as well, including Seattle, Chicago and New York; the intensifications are on course to make these areas unsuitable for outdoor activity <a href="#note-54">54</a> during the summer.</p>

<p>Recently generated predictive mapping <a href="#note-55">55</a> shows how many extremely hot days you might have to suffer through when you are older. These show clearly that if we continue along with business as usual – refusing to address ACD with the war-time-level response warranted to mitigate the damage – those being born now who will be here in 2100, will be experiencing heat extremes unlike anything we&rsquo;ve had to date when they venture outside in the summer.</p>

<p>Lastly for our air section, June was the third month in a row with global average carbon dioxide levels above 400 parts per million. Levels of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere haven&rsquo;t been this high <a href="#note-56">56</a> in somewhere between 800,000 and 15 million years.</p>

<p><strong>Fire</strong></p>

<p>A new study <a href="#note-32">32</a> published in Nature Geoscience revealed how increasing frequency and severity of forest fires across the planet are accelerating the melting of the Greenland ice sheet, as soot landing on the ice reduces its reflectivity. Melting at ever increasing speed, if the entire Greenland ice sheet melts, sea levels will rise 24 feet globally.</p>

<p>Down in Australia, the southern region of the country can now expect drier winters as a new study <a href="#note-57">57</a> linked drying trends there, which have been occurring over the last few decades, to ACD.</p>

<p>On the other side of the globe, in Canada&rsquo;s Northwest Territories, the region is battling its worst fires since the 1990s, bringing attention to the likelihood that ACD is amplifying the severity <a href="#note-58">58</a> of northern wildfires.</p>

<p>A recently published global atlas <a href="#note-59">59</a> of deaths and economic losses caused by wildfires, drought, flooding and other ACD-augmented weather extremes, revealed how such disasters are increasing worldwide, setting back development projects by years, if not decades, according to its publishers.</p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><strong>Denial and Reality</strong></p>

<p>Never underestimate the power of denial.</p>

<p>Rep. Jeff Miller (R-Florida) was asked by an MSNBC journalist if he was concerned about the fact that most voters believe scientists on the issue of ACD. His response, a page out of the Republican deniers handbook, is particularly impressive:</p>

<p><strong>Miller:</strong> It changes. It gets hot; it gets cold. It&rsquo;s done it for as long as we have measured the climate.</p>

<p><strong>MSNBC:</strong> But man-made, isn&rsquo;t that the question?</p>

<p><strong>Miller:</strong> Then why did the dinosaurs go extinct? Were there men that were causing – were there cars running around at that point, that were causing global warming? No. The climate has changed since earth was created.</p>

<p>Another impressive act of denial came from prominent Kentucky State Senate Majority Whip Republican Brandon Smith. At a recent hearing, Smith argued that carbon emissions from coal burning power plants couldn&rsquo;t possibly be causing ACD because Mars is also experiencing a global temperature rise, and there are no coal plants generating carbon emissions on Mars. He even stated that Mars was the same temperature of Earth.</p>

<p>&ldquo;I think that in academia, we all agree that the temperature on Mars is exactly as it is here. Nobody will dispute that,&rdquo; Smith said <a href="#note-60">60</a>.</p>

<p>On average, the temperature on Mars <a href="#note-61">61</a> is about minus 80 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Yet there are no coal mines on Mars; there&rsquo;s no factories on Mars that I&rsquo;m aware of,&rdquo; he added. &ldquo;So I think what we&rsquo;re looking at is something much greater than what we&rsquo;re going to do.&rdquo;</p>

<p>During a recent interview <a href="#note-62">62</a> on CNBC, Princeton University professor and chairman of the Marshall Institute William Happer was called out on the fact that ExxonMobil had provided nearly $1 million for the Institute.</p>

<p>Happer compared the &ldquo;hype&rdquo; about ACD to the Holocaust, and when asked about his 2009 comparison of climate science to Nazi propaganda, he said, &ldquo;The comment I made was, the demonization of carbon dioxide is just like the demonization of the poor Jews under Hitler. Carbon dioxide is actually a benefit to the world, and so were the Jews.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Happer, who was introduced as an &ldquo;industry expert&rdquo; on the program, has not published one peer-reviewed paper on ACD.</p>

<p>The ACD-denier group that supports politicians and &ldquo;scientists&rdquo; of this type, Heartland (a free-market think tank with a $6 million annual budget) hosted <a href="#note-63">63</a> a July conference in Las Vegas for deniers. One of Heartland&rsquo;s former funders is ExxonMobil, and one of the panels at the conference was titled, &ldquo;Global Warming As a Social Movement.&rdquo; The leaders of the conference vowed to &ldquo;keep doubt alive.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Australian Prime Minister Tony Abbott used a current trip abroad to attempt to build support for a coalition aimed at derailing <a href="#note-64">64</a> international efforts towards dealing with ACD.</p>

<p>He is simply following the lead of former Prime Minister John Howard, who teamed up with former US President George W. Bush and Canadian Prime Minister Stephen Harper to form a climate-denial triumvirate whose goal was to stop efforts aimed at dealing with ACD, in addition to working actively to undermine the Kyoto Protocol.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Rupert Murdoch has said <a href="#note-65">65</a> that ACD should be approached with great skepticism. He said <a href="#note-66">66</a> that if global temperatures increased 3 degrees Celsius over the next 100 years, &ldquo;At the very most one of those degrees would be man-made.&rdquo; He did not provide the science he used to generate this calculation.</p>

<p>In Canada, Vancouver-based Pacific Future Energy Corporation claimed <a href="#note-67">67</a> that a $10 billion oil sands refinery it wants to build on the coast of British Columbia would be the &ldquo;world&rsquo;s greenest.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Miami, a low-lying city literally on the front lines of ACD impacts, is being inundated by rising sea levels as its predominantly Republican leadership – made up of ACD deniers – are choosing to ignore the facts <a href="#note-68">68</a> and continue forward with major coastal construction projects.</p>

<p>Back to reality, the BBC recently ordered <a href="#note-69">69</a> its journalists to cease giving any more TV airtime to ACD deniers.</p>

<p>Brenton County, Oregon has created <a href="#note-70">70</a> a Climate Change Adaptation Plan that provides strategies for the communities there to deal with future impacts of ACD.</p>

<p>Despite the millions of dollars annually being pumped into ACD denial campaigns, a recent poll shows that by a 2-to-1 margin <a href="#note-71">71</a>, Americans would be willing to pay more to combat ACD impacts, and most would also vote to support a candidate who aims to address the issue.</p>

<p>Another recent report <a href="#note-72">72</a> on the economic costs that ACD is expected to generate in the United States over the next 25 years pegged an estimate well into the hundreds of billions of dollars by 2100. Property losses from hurricanes and coastal storms are expected to total around $35 billion, crop yields are expected to decline by 14 percent, and increased electricity costs to keep people cooler are expected to increase by $12 billion annually, to name a few examples.</p>

<p>The bipartisan report also noted that more than a million coastal homes and businesses could flood repeatedly before ultimately being destroyed.</p>

<p>The World Council on Churches, a group that represents more than half a billion Christians, announced <a href="#note-173">73</a> that it would pull all its investments out of fossil fuels because the investments were no longer &ldquo;ethical.&rdquo;</p>

<p>US Interior Secretary Sally Jewell told reporters <a href="#note-74">74</a> recently that she is witnessing ACD&rsquo;s impacts in practically every national park she visits.</p>

<p>A June report <a href="#note-75">75</a> by the UN University&rsquo;s Institute for Environment and Human Security warned that ACD-driven mass migrations are already happening, and urged countries to immediately create adaption plans to resettle populations and avoid conflict.</p>

<p>For anyone who wonders how much impact humans have on the planet on a daily basis, take a few moments to ponder what just the impact of commercial airline emissions are in a 24-hour period by watching this <a href="#note-76">76</a> astounding video.</p>

<p>Lastly, a landmark study released in June by an international group of scientists concluded that Earth is on the brink of a mass extinction event comparable in scale to that which caused the dinosaurs to go extinct 65 million years ago.</p>

<p>The study says extinction rates are now 1,000 times higher than normal, and pegged ACD as the driving cause.</p>

<p>Dahr Jamail, a Truthout staff reporter, is the author of <em>The Will to Resist: Soldiers Who Refuse to Fight in Iraq and Afghanistan</em>, (Haymarket Books, 2009), and <em>Beyond the Green Zone: Dispatches From an Unembedded Journalist in Occupied Iraq</em>, (Haymarket Books, 2007). Jamail reported from Iraq for more than a year, as well as from Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and Turkey over the last ten years, and has won the Martha Gellhorn Award for Investigative Journalism, among other awards.</p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><a id="note-1"></a> [1]: <a href="http://ds.data.jma.go.jp/tcc/tcc/products/gwp/temp/jun_wld.html">http://ds.data.jma.go.jp/tcc/tcc/products/gwp/temp/jun_wld.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-2"></a>[2]: <a href="http://mashable.com/2014/06/17/earth-warmest-may-spring/">http://mashable.com/2014/06/17/earth-warmest-may-spring/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-3"></a>[3]: <a href="http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/sotc/global/2014/5">http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/sotc/global/2014/5</a></p>

<p><a id="note-4"></a>[4]: <a href="http://www.newindianexpress.com/states/andhra_pradesh/AP-Heat-Wave-Claims-169-Lives-So-Far/2014/06/16/article2282910.ece">http://www.newindianexpress.com/states/andhra_pradesh/AP-Heat-Wave-Claims-169-Lives-So-Far/2014/06/16/article2282910.ece</a></p>

<p><a id="note-5"></a>[5]: <a href="http://www.accuweather.com/en/weather-news/hottest-air-so-far-this-year-b/28207678">http://www.accuweather.com/en/weather-news/hottest-air-so-far-this-year-b/28207678</a></p>

<p><a id="note-6"></a>[6]: <a href="http://blueandgreentomorrow.com/2014/06/04/deadly-heatwave-kills-four-and-hospitalises-1600-in-japan/">http://blueandgreentomorrow.com/2014/06/04/deadly-heatwave-kills-four-and-hospitalises-1600-in-japan/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-7"></a>[7]: <a href="http://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2014/02jul_oco2/">http://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2014/02jul_oco2/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-8"></a>[8]: <a href="http://www.heatisonline.org/contentserver/objecthandlers/index.cfm?ID=8588&amp;Method=Full">http://www.heatisonline.org/contentserver/objecthandlers/index.cfm?ID=8588&amp;Method=Full</a></p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><a id="note-8"></a>[9]: <a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2014/07/140701-global-warming-summer-climate-change-science/">http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2014/07/140701-global-warming-summer-climate-change-science/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-10"></a>[10]: <a href="http://www.trust.org/item/20140630145804-v85jo/?source=fiHeadlineStory">http://www.trust.org/item/20140630145804-v85jo/?source=fiHeadlineStory</a></p>

<p><a id="note-11"></a>[11]: <a href="http://www.desertsun.com/longform/news/environment/2014/05/31/global-warming-joshua-tree-national-park/9729285/">http://www.desertsun.com/longform/news/environment/2014/05/31/global-warming-joshua-tree-national-park/9729285/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-12"></a>[12]: <a href="http://www.adn.com/article/20140628/north-slope-birds-nesting-earlier-keep-pace-earlier-snowmelt-study-says">http://www.adn.com/article/20140628/north-slope-birds-nesting-earlier-keep-pace-earlier-snowmelt-study-says</a></p>

<p><a id="note-13"></a>[13]: <a href="http://www.nature.com/nclimate/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nclimate2280.html">http://www.nature.com/nclimate/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nclimate2280.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-14"></a>[14]: <a href="http://www.nature.com/srep/2014/140513/srep05024/full/srep05024.html">http://www.nature.com/srep/2014/140513/srep05024/full/srep05024.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-15"></a>[15]: <a href="http://www.globaloceancommission.org/wp-content/uploads/GOC_Report_20_6.FINAL_.spreads.pdf">http://www.globaloceancommission.org/wp-content/uploads/GOC_Report_20_6.FINAL_.spreads.pdf</a></p>

<p><a id="note-16"></a>[16]: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/06/10/science/of-fish-monsoons-and-the-future.html?_r=1">http://www.nytimes.com/2014/06/10/science/of-fish-monsoons-and-the-future.html?_r=1</a></p>

<p><a id="note-17"></a>[17]: <a href="http://www.wired.com/2014/06/absurd-creature-of-the-week-lions-mane-jellyfish/">http://www.wired.com/2014/06/absurd-creature-of-the-week-lions-mane-jellyfish/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-18"></a>[18]: <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/elements/2014/06/the-disappearing-islands-of-kiribati.html">http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/elements/2014/06/the-disappearing-islands-of-kiribati.html</a></p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><a id="note-19"></a>[19]: <a href="http://www.trust.org/item/20140609120036-fgtf8/">http://www.trust.org/item/20140609120036-fgtf8/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-20"></a>[20]: <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/video/index/372747/the-louisiana-town-devoured-by-climate-change/">http://www.theatlantic.com/video/index/372747/the-louisiana-town-devoured-by-climate-change/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-21"></a>[21]: <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/risky-business-climarte-change-us-obama-investors">http://www.theguardian.com/sustainable-business/risky-business-climarte-change-us-obama-investors</a></p>

<p><a id="note-22"></a>[22]: <a href="http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/lifestyle/hotter-and-larger-tropics/1219108.html">http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/lifestyle/hotter-and-larger-tropics/1219108.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-23"></a>[23]: <a href="http://newamericamedia.org/2014/06/oakland-at-risk-of-severe-floods---not-just-water-but-sewage.php">http://newamericamedia.org/2014/06/oakland-at-risk-of-severe-floods---not-just-water-but-sewage.php</a></p>

<p><a id="note-24"></a>[24]: <a href="http://www.postandcourier.com/article/20140622/PC16/140629900/1006/troubled-waters-second-punch-of-ocean-acidification-threatens-lowcountry">http://www.postandcourier.com/article/20140622/PC16/140629900/1006/troubled-waters-second-punch-of-ocean-acidification-threatens-lowcountry</a></p>

<p><a id="note-25"></a>[25]: <a href="http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/USA-Update/2014/0619/Record-floods-in-Midwest-may-be-part-of-larger-pattern-locals-say-video">http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/USA-Update/2014/0619/Record-floods-in-Midwest-may-be-part-of-larger-pattern-locals-say-video</a></p>

<p><a id="note-26"></a>[26]: <a href="http://www.adn.com/article/20140702/fairbanks-sees-14-average-annual-rainfall-24-hours">http://www.adn.com/article/20140702/fairbanks-sees-14-average-annual-rainfall-24-hours</a></p>

<p><a id="note-27"></a>[27]: <a href="http://qz.com/228284/the-ocean-is-swallowing-up-virginia-so-rapidly-that-its-leaders-are-forgetting-to-bicker-about-climate-change/">http://qz.com/228284/the-ocean-is-swallowing-up-virginia-so-rapidly-that-its-leaders-are-forgetting-to-bicker-about-climate-change/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-28"></a>[28]: <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/07/10/us-usa-sealevel-flood-idUSKBN0FF20220140710">http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/07/10/us-usa-sealevel-flood-idUSKBN0FF20220140710</a></p>

<p><a id="note-29"></a>[29]: <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/06/21/us-bulgaria-floods-idUSKBN0EW0KA20140621">http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/06/21/us-bulgaria-floods-idUSKBN0EW0KA20140621</a></p>

<p><a id="note-30"></a>[30]: <a href="http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/china/2014-06/21/content_17606604.htm">http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/china/2014-06/21/content_17606604.htm</a></p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><a id="note-31"></a>[31]: <a href="http://mashable.com/2014/06/11/global-warming-drought-flood-frequency/?utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_source=rss">http://mashable.com/2014/06/11/global-warming-drought-flood-frequency/?utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_source=rss</a></p>

<p><a id="note-32"></a>[32]: <a href="http://www.nature.com/ngeo/journal/v7/n7/full/ngeo2180.html">http://www.nature.com/ngeo/journal/v7/n7/full/ngeo2180.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-33"></a>[33]: <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-27831958">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-27831958</a></p>

<p><a id="note-34"></a>[34]: <a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2014/06/140609-arctic-ice-maps-atlas-tenth-edition-science/">http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2014/06/140609-arctic-ice-maps-atlas-tenth-edition-science/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-35"></a>[35]: <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-27870459">http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-27870459</a></p>

<p><a id="note-36"></a>[36]: <a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/canada-struggles-with-melting-permafrost-as-climate-warms/">http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/canada-struggles-with-melting-permafrost-as-climate-warms/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-37"></a>[37]: <a href="http://www.dailyclimate.org/tdc-newsroom/2014/07/arctic-bird-breeding">http://www.dailyclimate.org/tdc-newsroom/2014/07/arctic-bird-breeding</a></p>

<p><a id="note-38"></a>[38]: <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2014/jul/05/dark-snow-speeding-glacier-melting-rising-sea-levels">http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2014/jul/05/dark-snow-speeding-glacier-melting-rising-sea-levels</a></p>

<p><a id="note-39"></a>[39]: <a href="http://www.latimes.com/local/la-me-drought-grazing-20140616-story.html#page=1">http://www.latimes.com/local/la-me-drought-grazing-20140616-story.html#page=1</a></p>

<p><a id="note-40"></a>[40]: <a href="http://www.deseretnews.com/article/865605117/Dried-up-poverty-in-Americas-drought-lands.html?pg=all">http://www.deseretnews.com/article/865605117/Dried-up-poverty-in-Americas-drought-lands.html?pg=all</a></p>

<p><a id="note-41"></a>[41]: <a href="http://www.climatecentral.org/news/californias-drought-just-got-a-little-worse-17586">http://www.climatecentral.org/news/californias-drought-just-got-a-little-worse-17586</a></p>

<p><a id="note-42"></a>[42]: <a href="http://blogs.kqed.org/science/audio/california-drought-dries-up-honey-supply/">http://blogs.kqed.org/science/audio/california-drought-dries-up-honey-supply/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-43"></a>[43]: <a href="http://www.mercurynews.com/drought/ci_26009266/california-drought-snowmelt-path-shows-impact-sierras-pacific">http://www.mercurynews.com/drought/ci_26009266/california-drought-snowmelt-path-shows-impact-sierras-pacific</a></p>

<p><a id="note-44"></a>[44]: <a href="http://tucson.com/news/science/environment/tucson-other-cities-could-be-hit-by-cap-shortage-much/article_795728a5-2884-5d2f-b64d-d60b504ec8fc.html">http://tucson.com/news/science/environment/tucson-other-cities-could-be-hit-by-cap-shortage-much/article_795728a5-2884-5d2f-b64d-d60b504ec8fc.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-45"></a>[45]: <a href="http://www.desertsun.com/story/news/environment/2014/07/13/lake-mead-water-levels/12608677/">http://www.desertsun.com/story/news/environment/2014/07/13/lake-mead-water-levels/12608677/</a></p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><a id="note-46"></a>[46]: <a href="http://www.latimes.com/business/hiltzik/la-fi-hiltzik-20140620-column.html#page=1">http://www.latimes.com/business/hiltzik/la-fi-hiltzik-20140620-column.html#page=1</a></p>

<p><a id="note-47"></a>[47]: <a href="http://www.desertsun.com/longform/news/environment/2014/06/14/global-warming-southwest-water-supply-drought/10418637/">http://www.desertsun.com/longform/news/environment/2014/06/14/global-warming-southwest-water-supply-drought/10418637/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-48"></a>[48]: <a href="http://www.trust.org/item/20140623092801-ocjsh/?source=fiOtherNews2">http://www.trust.org/item/20140623092801-ocjsh/?source=fiOtherNews2</a></p>

<p><a id="note-49"></a>[49]: <a href="http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/8e42bdc8-0838-11e4-9afc-00144feab7de.html#slide0">http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/8e42bdc8-0838-11e4-9afc-00144feab7de.html#slide0</a></p>

<p><a id="note-50"></a>[50]: <a href="http://tucson.com/news/science/environment/study-rising-az-temperatures-make-for-hostile-environment/article_f95aa84b-13a4-5f84-9944-2d092c8647cc.html">http://tucson.com/news/science/environment/study-rising-az-temperatures-make-for-hostile-environment/article_f95aa84b-13a4-5f84-9944-2d092c8647cc.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-51"></a>[51]: <a href="http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/06/23/too-hot-to-handle/">http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/06/23/too-hot-to-handle/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-52"></a>[52]: <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/life/health-and-fitness/health/canadas-most-pressing-health-issue-is-climate-change-public-health-experts/article19186733/">http://www.theglobeandmail.com/life/health-and-fitness/health/canadas-most-pressing-health-issue-is-climate-change-public-health-experts/article19186733/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-53"></a>[53]: <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/science/environment/cough-cough-climate-change-may-worsen-air-pollution-n136986">http://www.nbcnews.com/science/environment/cough-cough-climate-change-may-worsen-air-pollution-n136986</a></p>

<p><a id="note-54"></a>[54]: <a href="http://planetark.org/enviro-news/item/71775">http://planetark.org/enviro-news/item/71775</a></p>

<p><a id="note-55"></a>[55]: <a href="http://climatedesk.org/2014/06/these-maps-show-how-many-brutally-hot-days-you-will-suffer-when-youre-old/">http://climatedesk.org/2014/06/these-maps-show-how-many-brutally-hot-days-you-will-suffer-when-youre-old/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-56"></a>[56]: <a href="http://www.climatecentral.org/news/co2-milestone-400-ppm-climate-17692">http://www.climatecentral.org/news/co2-milestone-400-ppm-climate-17692</a></p>

<p><a id="note-57"></a>[57]: <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/environment/climate-change/australias-dry-south-to-become-even-drier-scientists-say-20140713-zt650.html">http://www.smh.com.au/environment/climate-change/australias-dry-south-to-become-even-drier-scientists-say-20140713-zt650.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-58"></a>[58]: <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/what-wildfires-in-the-northwest-territories-say-about-climate-change/article19606467/">http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/what-wildfires-in-the-northwest-territories-say-about-climate-change/article19606467/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-59"></a>[59]: <a href="http://www.trust.org/item/20140711144054-h9pbj/">http://www.trust.org/item/20140711144054-h9pbj/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-60"></a>[60]: <a href="http://www.ket.org/legislature/archives/">http://www.ket.org/legislature/archives/</a></p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>

<p><a id="note-61"></a>[61]: <a href="http://www.space.com/16907-what-is-the-temperature-of-mars.html">http://www.space.com/16907-what-is-the-temperature-of-mars.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-62"></a>[62]: <a href="http://mediamatters.org/blog/2014/07/15/cnbcs-climate-expert-demonization-of-carbon-dio/200107">http://mediamatters.org/blog/2014/07/15/cnbcs-climate-expert-demonization-of-carbon-dio/200107</a></p>

<p><a id="note-63"></a>[63]: <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-07-10/in-las-vegas-climate-change-deniers-re-group-vow-to-keep-doubt-alive.html">http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-07-10/in-las-vegas-climate-change-deniers-re-group-vow-to-keep-doubt-alive.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-64"></a>[64]: <a href="http://www.theage.com.au/federal-politics/political-news/tony-abbott-seeks-alliance-to-thwart-president-obama-on-climate-change-policy-20140609-39t93.html">http://www.theage.com.au/federal-politics/political-news/tony-abbott-seeks-alliance-to-thwart-president-obama-on-climate-change-policy-20140609-39t93.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-65"></a>[65]: <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/media/2014/jul/13/rupert-murdoch-labors-nbn-was-ridiculous">http://www.theguardian.com/media/2014/jul/13/rupert-murdoch-labors-nbn-was-ridiculous</a></p>

<p><a id="note-66"></a>[66]: <a href="http://www.theage.com.au/national/fight-climate-change-by-building-away-from-sea-rupert-murdoch-20140713-zt66s.html">http://www.theage.com.au/national/fight-climate-change-by-building-away-from-sea-rupert-murdoch-20140713-zt66s.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-67"></a>[67]: <a href="http://business.financialpost.com/2014/06/10/pacific-future-bc-refinery/?__lsa=6ae8-54ff">http://business.financialpost.com/2014/06/10/pacific-future-bc-refinery/?__lsa=6ae8-54ff</a></p>

<p><a id="note-68"></a>[68]: <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/11/miami-drowning-climate-change-deniers-sea-levels-rising">http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/11/miami-drowning-climate-change-deniers-sea-levels-rising</a></p>

<p><a id="note-69"></a>[69]: <a href="http://downloads.bbc.co.uk/bbctrust/assets/files/pdf/our_work/science_impartiality/trust_conclusions.pdf">http://downloads.bbc.co.uk/bbctrust/assets/files/pdf/our_work/science_impartiality/trust_conclusions.pdf</a></p>

<p><a id="note-70"></a>[70]: <a href="http://www.gazettetimes.com/news/local/bracing-for-impact/article_4e1cf990-0313-11e4-90c2-001a4bcf887a.html">http://www.gazettetimes.com/news/local/bracing-for-impact/article_4e1cf990-0313-11e4-90c2-001a4bcf887a.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-71"></a>[71]: <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-06-10/americans-by-2-to-1-would-pay-more-to-curb-climate-change.html">http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-06-10/americans-by-2-to-1-would-pay-more-to-curb-climate-change.html</a></p>

<p><a id="note-72"></a>[72]: <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/06/24/us-climatechange-economy-idUSKBN0EZ0AA20140624">http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/06/24/us-climatechange-economy-idUSKBN0EZ0AA20140624</a></p>

<p><a id="note-73"></a>[73]: <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/GEN_FIN06_APPROVED_Report_Finance_Policy_Committee.pdf">http://thinkprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/GEN_FIN06_APPROVED_Report_Finance_Policy_Committee.pdf</a></p>

<p><a id="note-74"></a>[74]: <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2014/06/30/capital-download-interior-secretary-sally-jewell-climate-change-national-parks/11778421/">http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2014/06/30/capital-download-interior-secretary-sally-jewell-climate-change-national-parks/11778421/</a></p>

<p><a id="note-75"></a>[75]: <a href="http://ehs.unu.edu/file/get/11786.pdf">http://ehs.unu.edu/file/get/11786.pdf</a></p>

<p><a id="note-76"></a>[76]: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G1L4GUA8arY">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G1L4GUA8arY</a></p>

<p><em><a href="#topOfArticle">Back to top</a></em></p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  
	
  
	
  
	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[European Elections 2014 in France: 2 presentations.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/06/02/European-Elections-2014-2-results/"/>
	    <updated>2014-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/06/02/European-Elections-2014-2-results/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>by Patrick Toca - 2 June 2014</em></p>

<hr />

<h1>Abstention, the first Party and by far&hellip;</h1>

<h1>&hellip; systematically ignored.</h1>

<hr>

<div id="chartdiv1" style="width: 100%; height: 400px;"></div>
<hr>
<div id="chartdiv2" style="width: 100%; height: 400px;"></div>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/panel-3.jpg" alt="elections-2014" title="A lulling song and good children go to heaven." />
</p>

<hr />
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elections of April 2014 in France: a dissident interpretation of results.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/05/05/about-the-french-elections-avril-2014/"/>
	    <updated>2014-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/05/05/about-the-french-elections-avril-2014/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/moebius-arzac-750.jpg" alt="Elections" title="Capitalism" />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by Patrick Toca - May 11, 2014</h2>

<hr />

<p>Abstentionism: Have the elections results interpretation become but a means to maintain alive obsolete mantras about institutions the people expects nothing from ? What does the people tell when it abstains ?</p>

<hr />

<h1>Elections of April 2014 in France: a dissident interpretation of results</h1>

<h2>Table of Contents</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="#1">What elections are in France</a></li>
<li><a href="#2">Recent experiences: awareness raising</a></li>
<li><a href="#3">April 2014 elections results: the true data</a></li>
<li><a href="#4">An interpretation based on hidden facts</a></li>
<li><a href="#5">A gambit to be confirmed by incoming European elections</a>

<ul>
<li><a href="#6">The collapse of old parties confirmed</a></li>
<li><a href="#7">The dissident movement is structuring itself</a></li>
<li><a href="#8">A common understanding becoming clearer</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<h2><a name='1'>What elections are in France</a></h2>

<p>In France there are 3 main elections:</p>

<p>The <strong>presidential one</strong> organizes the election of the french President: this latter &ldquo;institution&rdquo; will garner more &lsquo;un-controlled&rsquo; power than the USA president. This election occurs every 5 years, it takes place in 2 rounds at the majority. The mechanisms promotes bi-partism.</p>

<p>The <strong>&ldquo;legislatives&rdquo; one</strong> (legislature) organizes the election of the Members of the Parliament&rsquo;s Assembly Nationale (lower house): this &ldquo;institution&rdquo; is meant to vote the laws. it takes place in 2 rounds at the majority. The parliament is composed of 577 members and is totally renewed every 5 years. This election is planned just after (one month) the Presidential one, in order to secure a legislature that is coherent with the president policy. Mono-partism is enforced.</p>

<p>The <strong>&ldquo;municipales&rdquo; one</strong> organizes the election of the municipal councils of France&rsquo;s communes. The first task of each newly constituted municipal council is to elect a mayor for that commune. This election occurs every 6 years and is a list based votation. The number of council members varies from 7 to 69 according to the size of the commune. The council members will elect the members of the Parliament&rsquo;s upper house: the french Senate (348 members).</p>

<p>These are institutions of a representative government and the powers respectively granted to each of them, defines what is called a Presidential system.</p>

<p>The present system has come out of the Coup d&rsquo;Etat of 13 May 1958, which has ended the 4th Republic (parliamentary system, that begun in 1946 just after the WWII) and started the 5th Republic in October 1958 (presidential system).</p>

<p>What is important to know for the moment, is that a larger and larger part of the french population is skeptical about these elections and its consequences. As a matter of fact, what characterizes most the recent history of french elections is the growing percentage of &ldquo;abstentionists&rdquo;, now and since at least 25 years the first actual &lsquo;party&rsquo; of any election.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s observe that this &lsquo;abstentionism&rsquo; is rarely properly analyzed.</p>

<h6>to be mentioned here</h6>

<hr />

<p>Since the events of 2005-2007 (I will briefly come back to it later) a first knowledge is gaining momentum in France: that the representative governments are not democracies, but aristocracies (a forgotten fact that was well known by Montesquieu, Rousseau or Sieyès in their time). This understanding has been refreshed by B.Manin (The Principles of Representative Government, 1997) who reminds us that while today representative institutions and democracy appear as virtually indistinguishable, when representative government was first established in Europe and America, it was designed in opposition to democracy proper.</p>

<hr />

<p>Is the legitimacy of these institutions challenged ?</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/revolte-or-not.jpg" alt="People's voice" title="People's voice." />
</p>

<hr />

<h2><a name='2'>Recent experiences: awareness raising</a></h2>

<p>For the last 30 years (thirty !), abstentionism set a new record at each election (only the presidential has had a narrow escape from this terrible rule). During the 1983 &ldquo;municipales&rdquo;, 20,3% of registered voters had abstained; last march, 37,8% did.</p>

<p>If one add to these abstentionists all those who are not registered on voting lists (in France it is a requisite to go and register voluntarily. It is not automatic as in England. As a consequence about 7% of potential voters are not on the voting lists.), then abstentionism is getting close to 50% for European, Legislature and &ldquo;Municipales&rdquo; elections.</p>

<p>This situation is more striking in large cities, where voting are by far the minority: during the first round of 2014 &ldquo;municipales&rdquo;, in towns of more than 100.000 inhabitants, the official participation has been 53,8%, but if you add non registered people, a minority has actually voted.</p>

<p>This is all the more significant that according to Insee (Institut National de la statistique et des études économiques) the discriminants of &ldquo;voting/not voting&rdquo; are highly marked socially wise. As an example, youth are voting 2 times less than seniors: 41,2% of 18-24 years old are voting compare to 80.2% of 50-64 years old.</p>

<p>Complementary, the voting group is the one the least impacted by precarious jobs and social difficulties.</p>

<p>The voting minority is not representative of the population.</p>

<p>When one observes that in most cases previous elected MPs are rarely re-elected, and mainly because their voting fans have preferred to abstain (since no change actually occurred in spite of a so called alternating promised policy), a correlation should be validated between &ldquo;No-Change Alternating the MPs&rdquo; and &ldquo;Abstentionism&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Abstentionism is certainly the most important artefact of the French elections, yet almost no serious analysis exist about its signification.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s dare to think that abstentionism is an indicator of the raising awareness that the &lsquo;representative governement institutions&rsquo; are unable to deliver the population&rsquo;s expectations.</p>

<h6>to be recalled here</h6>

<hr />

<p>The 2005-2007 Coup d&rsquo;Etat.</p>

<p>The 2005 referendum was to decide whether or not the European Constitution should be accepted. After months of debates, numerous people&rsquo;s local assemblies and popular self-education, in spite of a massive propaganda for a YES by both UMP and PS with the media support (TV, newspapers and radios), the result had been NO. Abstentionism: was less than 16%, the lowest in recent votation history. The NO gathered more than 54%, a total legitimacy!</p>

<p><strong>Memorable argument</strong>: would you sign any contract that is 493 articles long, that not even lawyers are able to decipher and understand ?</p>

<p>Then, in 2007, following the recent election of N.Sarkozy (UMP), convened in a Congress (lower and upper houses together) the Members of Parliament (UMP + PS) garnered a majority of more than the 66% required by law to enforce a YES to a strict clone of the previous rejected European Constitution renamed Lisbon Treaty.</p>

<p><strong>Lesson learned</strong>: whatever people&rsquo;s vote will be, the &ldquo;pseudo&rdquo;-representants are ready to do the contrary! For the interest of who ?</p>

<hr />

<h2><a name='3'>April 2014 elections results: the true data</a></h2>

<p>In spite of a literally &ldquo;massive flood of information&rdquo; about the rise of Extreme Right and Right, the facts seem to contradict this communication outburst.</p>

<p>Based on the total number of registered voting persons, the &ldquo;raise of FN&rdquo; appears quite relative: In the 2012 elections, Ms Le Pen cornered 12%. In 2014, the FN has just gathered 8% during the 2014 &ldquo;municipales&rdquo; elections. Yet, it is true that the FN has progressed in terms of town conquered!</p>

<p>Same conclusion about the other traditional Right, UMP. Even though it has gained 62 towns of more than 10.000 inhabitants, one of its best success during the 5th Republic, it has in fact gathered less votations in 2014 than in 2008!</p>

<p>In fact, abstentionism has raised massively and the Socialist Party (the &lsquo;deceptive&rsquo; pseudo-Left or &lsquo;complexed&rsquo; new Right, according to certain french thinkers - Lordon, Badiou, Sapir) has seen a lot of its traditional voting fans refusing to support its neo-liberal actual policy.</p>

<p>The recent new movement (a gathering of 9 political parties: PCF, PG, Ensemble) named Front de Gauche (created in late 2008) has been the only one to slightly improve its position: 12% in 2014 compare to 11% in 2012. But this has hardly ever been mentioned in the media. An important situation is to be noted: during these elections, a part of the PCF direction has chosen, in some towns (50% of them in fact!), to abandon the FdG (that they contributed to found) and join  opportunistically the PS (as a direct consequence, the PCF has known one of its more memorable disaster and lost many of its long hold towns to the Right and the FdG credibility been put in question.)</p>

<h6>TODOS</h6>

<hr />

<p>The media have proven to play a political role more than an informative one during these elections.</p>

<p>In particular, the CSA () gave this information:</p>

<p>Relevés du temps d&rsquo;antenne au 24 février publié par le CSA. Voir sur le site du CSA, ici: <a href="http://www.csa.fr/Television/Le-suivi-des-programmes/Le-pluralisme-politique-et-les-campagnes-electorales/Elections-municipales-2014-temps-de-parole">http://www.csa.fr/Television/Le-suivi-des-programmes/Le-pluralisme-politique-et-les-campagnes-electorales/Elections-municipales-2014-temps-de-parole</a></p>

<p>En résumé : la situation se dégrade pour le Front de Gauche à la télé. 6% du temps pour le Front de Gauche alors qu&rsquo;on trouvait 7% au précédant relevé le 10 février dernier.</p>

<p>A la radio la situation frémit légèrement pour le Fdg : 6,6% du temps contre 5% au 10 février.</p>

<p>Mais le cumul PS/UMP/EELV est toujours très élevé 75%.</p>

<p>==========</p>

<p>Les temps de parole relevés par le Conseil Supérieur de l’Audiovisuel entre le 10 février et le 7 mars (période ou l’équité entre les candidats n’est pas imposée) montrent que le pluralisme est violé; que la démocratie est en danger; que le Front National est favorisé; que le Front de Gauche est censuré.</p>

<p>Télévisions:
    TODOS as infographic</p>

<p>TF1: UMP 100%</p>

<p>France 2: FN 26,12%; PS 25,30%; UMP 23,75%; LO 14,37%; Debout la République 5,72%; Parti Radical 3,14%; EELV 1,60%; Front de Gauche 0%</p>

<p>France 3: FN 48,71%; UMP 23,23%; LO 12,74%; EELV 7,90%; PS 7,42%; Front de Gauche 0%.</p>

<p>France 5: FN 65,15%; UMP 34,85%; Front de Gauche 0%</p>

<p>Canal+ (infos): FN 100%; Front de gauche 0%</p>

<p>Canal+ (programmes): UMP 61,35%; EELV 19%; FN 16,38%; PS 3,28%; Front de Gauche 0%</p>

<p>RMC Découverte: FN 69,62%; PS 18,99%; UMP 11,39%; Front de gauche 0%</p>

<p>BFM TV: FN: 42,98% du temps ; PS 17,64%; UMP 15,86%; Parti de Gauche 9,26%; MODEM 4,85%; PCF 3,37%.</p>

<p>I-Télé: UMP 41,15%; PS 20,79%; FN 15,05%; LO 7,74%; EELV 5,96%; UDI 3,56%; PG 2,80%; PCF 2,33%.</p>

<p>LCI: PS 38,86%; UMP 27%; FN 19,04%; MODEM 6,64%; PG 5,47; EELV 2,90%; Debout la république 0,08%; PCF 0%.</p>

<p>==========</p>

<hr />

<h2><a name='4'>An interpretation based on hidden facts</a></h2>

<p>We.</p>

<h2><a name='5'>A gambit to be confirmed by incoming European elections</a></h2>

<p>Alright, so we&rsquo;ve got our theory down pat, and it&rsquo;s time to start firing our massive s-expression-spewing assault rifles. First things first, we have to define our nodes:</p>

<pre><code>TODOS
</code></pre>

<p>For those of you unfamiliar with pylisp, this will define a class with fields <code>p</code>, <code>key</code>, and so on, and provide a basic constructor for this class.</p>

<h3><a name='6'>The collapse of old parties confirmed</a></h3>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s get cracking. First up is lookup, that is, the <code>get</code> function. Simple enough. Since our treap is already a binary tree, we can use the standard binary tree lookup algorithm, completely ignoring priorities:</p>

<pre><code>TODOS
</code></pre>

<p>Simple enough, eh? What about containment? Oh, it&rsquo;s even easier:</p>

<h3><a name='7'>The dissident movement is structuring itself</a></h3>

<pre><code>TODOS
</code></pre>

<h3><a name='8'>A common understanding becoming clearer</a></h3>

<pre><code>TODOS
</code></pre>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bell Labs and CSP Threads.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/03/19/Bell-Labs-and-CSP-Threads/"/>
	    <updated>2014-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2014/03/19/Bell-Labs-and-CSP-Threads/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://swtch.com/~rsc/thread/" target="_blank">original document</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/me.jpg" alt="CSP Threads" title="Bell Labs and CSP Threads" />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by Russ Cox - read - March 19, 2014</h2>

<h1>Bell Labs and CSP Threads</h1>

<p><strong>Introduction</strong></p>

<p>This page is a slice of the history of concurrent programming, focusing on one particular lineage of Hoare&rsquo;s language of communicating sequential processes (CSP) <a href="http://swtch.com#1"><a href="http://swtch.com/~rsc/">1</a></a> <a href="http://swtch.com#1a">[1a]</a>. Concurrent programming in this style is interesting for reasons not of efficiency but of clarity. That is, it is a widespread mistake to think only of concurrent programming as a means to increase performance, <em>e.g.</em>, to overlap disk I/O requests, to reduce latency by prefetching results to expected queries, or to take advantage of multiple processors. Such advantages are important but not relevant to this discussion. After all, they can be realized in other styles, such as asynchronous event-driven programming. Instead, we are interested in concurrent programming because it provides a natural abstraction that can make some programs much simpler.</p>

<p><strong>What this is not</strong></p>

<p>Most computer science undergraduates are forced to read Andrew Birrell&rsquo;s [“An Introduction to Programming with Threads.”]The SRC threads model is the one used by most thread packages currently available. The problem with all of these is that they are too low-level. Unlike the communication primitive provided by Hoare, the primitives in the SRC-style threading module must be combined with other techniques, usually shared memory, in order to be used effectively. In general, programmers tend not to build their own higher-level constructs, and are left frustrated by needing to pay attention to such low-level details.</p>

<p>For the moment, push Birrell&rsquo;s tutorial out of your mind. This is a different thread model. If you approach it as a different thread model, you may well find it much easier to understand.</p>

<p><strong>Communicating Sequential Processes</strong></p>

<p>By 1978, there were many proposed methods in use for communication and synchronization in the context of programming multiprocessors. Shared memory was the most common communication mechanism, and semaphores, critical regions, and monitors were among the synchronization mechanisms. C. A. R. Hoare addressed both issues with a single language primitive: synchronous communication. In Hoare&rsquo;s CSP language, processes communicate by sending or receiving values from named unbuffered channels. Since the channels are unbuffered, the send operation blocks until the value has been transferred to a receiver, thus providing a mechanism for synchronization.</p>

<p>One of Hoare&rsquo;s examples is that of reformatting 80-column cards for printing on a 125-column printer. In his solution, one process reads a card at a time, sending the disassembled contents character by character to a second process. This second process assembles groups of 125 characters, sending the groups to the line printer. This sounds trivial, but in the absence of buffered I/O libraries, the necessary bookkeeping involved in a single-process solution is onerous. In fact, buffered I/O libraries are really just encapsulations of these two sorts of processes that export the single-character communication interface.</p>

<p>As another example, which Hoare credits to Doug McIlroy, consider the generation of all primes less than a thousand. The sieve of Eratosthenes can be simulated by a pipeline of processes executing the following pseudocode:</p>

<pre><code>p = get a number from left neighbor
print p
loop:
    n = get a number from left neighbor
    if (p does not divide n)
        send n to right neighbor
</code></pre>

<p>A generating process can feed the numbers 2, 3, 4, &hellip;, 1000 into the left end of the pipeline: the first process in the line eliminates the multiples of 2, the second eliminates the multiples of 3, the third eliminates the multiples of 5, and so on:</p>

<p>The linear pipeline nature of the examples thus far is misrepresentative of the general nature of CSP, but even restricted to linear pipelines, the model is quite powerful. The power has been forcefully demonstrated by the success of the filter-and-pipeline approach for which the Unix operating system is well known <a href="http://swtch.com#2"><a href="http://science.webhostinggeeks.com/bell-laboratorije">2</a></a> Indeed, pipelines predate Hoare&rsquo;s paper. In an internal Bell Labs memo dated October 11, 1964, Doug McIlroy was toying with ideas that would become Unix pipelines: “We should have some ways of coupling programs like garden hose&ndash;screw in another segment when it becomes necessary to massage data in another way. This is the way of IO also.” <a href="http://swtch.com#3"><a href="http://swtch.com#1">3</a></a></p>

<p>Hoare&rsquo;s communicating processes are more general than typical Unix shell pipelines, since they can be connected in arbitrary patterns. In fact, Hoare gives as an example a 3x3 matrix of processes somewhat like the prime sieve that can be used to multiply a vector by a 3x3 square matrix.</p>

<p>Of course, the Unix pipe mechanism doesn&rsquo;t require the linear layout; only the shell syntax does. McIlroy reports toying with syntax for a shell with general plumbing early on but not liking the syntax enough to implement it (personal communication, 2011). Later shells did support some restricted forms of non-linear pipelines. Rochkind&rsquo;s 2dsh supports dags; Tom Duff&rsquo;s rc supports trees.</p>

<p>Hoare&rsquo;s language was novel and influential, but lacking in a few key aspects. The main defect is that the unbuffered channels used for communication are not first-class objects: they cannot be stored in variables, passed as arguments to functions, or sent across channels. As a result of this, the communication structure must be fixed while writing the program. Hence we must write a program to print the first 1000 primes rather than the first <em>n</em> primes, and to multiply a vector by a 3x3 matrix rather than an <em>n_x_n</em> matrix.</p>

<p><strong>Pan and Promela</strong></p>

<p>In 1980, barely two years after Hoare&rsquo;s paper, Gerard Holzmann and Rob Pike created a protocol analyzer called pan that takes a CSP dialect as input. Pan&rsquo;s CSP dialect had concatenation, selection, and looping, but no variables. Even so, Holzmann reports that “Pan found its first error in a Bell Labs data-switch control protocol on 21 November 1980. ” <a href="http://swtch.com#14"><a href="http://swtch.com#8">14</a></a>. That dialect may well have been the first CSP language at Bell Labs, and it certainly provided Pike with experience using and implementing a CSP-like language, his first of many.</p>

<p>Holzmann&rsquo;s protocol analyzer developed into the Spin model checker and its Promela language, which features first-class channels in the same way as Newsqueak (q.v.).</p>

<p><strong>Newsqueak</strong></p>

<p>Moving in a different direction, Luca Cardelli and Rob Pike developed the ideas in CSP into the Squeak mini-language <a href="http://swtch.com#4"><a href="http://swtch.com#1a">4</a></a> for generating user interface code. (This Squeak is distinct from the Squeak Smalltalk implementation.) Pike later expanded Squeak into the fully-fledged programming language Newsqueak <a href="http://swtch.com#5">11</a> which begat Plan 9&rsquo;s Alef <a href="http://swtch.com#7"><a href="http://swtch.com#2">7</a></a> <a href="http://swtch.com#8"><a href="http://swtch.com#3">8</a></a>, Inferno&rsquo;s Limbo <a href="http://swtch.com#9"><a href="http://swtch.com#14">9</a></a>, and Google&rsquo;s Go <a href="http://swtch.com#13"><a href="http://swtch.com#7">13</a></a>. The main semantic advantage of Newsqueak over Squeak is that Newsqueak treats communications channels as first-class objects: unlike in CSP and Squeak, channels <em>can</em> be stored in variables, passed as arguments to functions, and sent across channels. This in turn enables the programmatic construction of the communication structure, thus allowing the creation of more complex structures than would be reasonable to design by hand. In particular, Doug McIlroy demonstrated how the communication facilities of Newsqueak can be employed to write elegant programs for manipulating symbolic power series <a href="http://swtch.com#10"><a href="http://swtch.com#4">10</a></a>. Similar attempts in traditional languages tend to mire in bookkeeping. In a similar vein, Rob Pike demonstrated how the communication facilities can be employed to break out of the common event-based programming model, writing a concurrent window system <a href="http://swtch.com#11"><a href="http://swtch.com#5">11</a></a>.</p>

<p><strong>Alef</strong></p>

<p>Alef <a href="http://swtch.com#7"><a href="http://swtch.com#2">7</a></a> <a href="http://swtch.com#8"><a href="http://swtch.com#3">8</a></a> was a language designed by Phil Winterbottom to apply the Newsqueak ideas to a full-fledged systems programming language. Alef has two types of what we have been calling processes: procs and threads. The program is organized into one or more procs, which are shared-memory operating system processes that can be preemptively scheduled. Each proc contains one or more tasks, which are cooperatively scheduled coroutines. Note that each task is assigned to a particular proc: they do not migrate between procs.</p>

<p>The main use of procs is to provide contexts that can block for I/O independently of the main tasks. (Plan 9 has no select call, and even on Unix you need multiple procs if you want to overlap computation with non-network I/O.) The Acme paper <a href="http://swtch.com#12">19</a> has a nice brief discussion of procs and threads, as do [the lecture notes about the Plan 9 window system], also mentioned below.</p>

<p><strong>Limbo</strong></p>

<p>The Inferno operating system is a Plan 9 spinoff intended for set-top boxes. Its programming language, Limbo <a href="http://swtch.com#9"><a href="http://swtch.com#14">9</a></a>, was heavily influenced by Alef. It removed the distinction between procs and tasks, effectively having just procs, though they were of lighter weight than what most people think of as processes. All parallelism is preemptive. It is interesting that despite this, the language provides no real support for locking. Instead, the channel communication typically provides enough synchronization and encourages programmers to arrange that there is always a clear owner for any piece of data. Explicit locking is unnecessary.</p>

<p><strong>Libthread</strong></p>

<p>Back in the Plan 9 world, the Alef compilers turned out to be difficult to maintain as Plan 9 was ported to ever more architectures. Libthread was originally created to port Alef programs to C, so that the Alef compilers could be retired. Alef&rsquo;s procs and tasks are called procs and threads in libthread. The [manual page] is the definitive reference.</p>

<p><strong>Go</strong></p>

<p>Rob Pike and Ken Thompson moved on to Google and placed CSP at the center of the Go language&rsquo;s concurrency support.</p>

<p><strong>Getting Started</strong></p>

<p>To get a feel for the model, especially how processes and threads interact, it is worth reading the Alef User&rsquo;s Guide <a href="http://swtch.com#8"><a href="http://swtch.com#3">8</a></a>. The first thirty slides of this presentation<a href="http://wwwhome.cs.utwente.nl/~sape/gos/chap15.pdf">23</a> are a good introduction to how Alef constructs are represented in C.</p>

<p>The best examples of the power of the CSP model are McIlroy&rsquo;s and Pike&rsquo;s papers, mentioned above <a href="http://swtch.com#10"><a href="http://swtch.com#4">10</a></a> <a href="http://swtch.com#11"><a href="http://swtch.com#5">11</a></a>.</p>

<p>Rob Pike&rsquo;s home page contains lecture notes from a course on concurrent programming: an [introduction], and slides about the two aforementioned papers: [squinting] and [window system]. The last of the three provides a good example of how Plan 9 programs typically use procs and tasks.</p>

<p>Rob Pike gave a tech talk at Google<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jgVhBThJdXc">27</a> that provides a good introduction (57 minute video).</p>

<p>Rob Pike&rsquo;s half of his 2010 Google I/O talk with Russ Cox<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jgVhBThJdXc">27</a> shows how to use channels and Go&rsquo;s concurrency to implement a load balancing work management system.</p>

<p><strong>Related Resources</strong></p>

<p>John Reppy<a href="http://www.cs.uchicago.edu/~jhr">28</a> has applied the same ideas to ML, producing Concurrent ML<a href="http://cml.cs.uchicago.edu/">29</a>. He used CML to build, among other things, the eXene<a href="http://people.cs.uchicago.edu/~jhr/eXene/">30</a> multithreaded (non-event-driven) X Window System toolkit.</p>

<p><strong>References</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com/~rsc/">1</a> C. A. R. Hoare, “Communicating Sequential Processes,” <em>Communications of the ACM</em> 21(8) (August 1978), 666-677.</p>

<p>[1a]C. A. R. Hoare, <em>Communicating Sequential Processes</em>. Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey, 1985.</p>

<p><a href="http://science.webhostinggeeks.com/bell-laboratorije">2</a> Michael S. Mahoney, ed.,  <em>The Unix Oral History Project, Release 0: The Beginning</em> <a href="http://www.princeton.edu/~hos/Mahoney/expotape.htm">31</a></p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#1">3</a> M. Douglas McIlroy, internal Bell Labs memorandum, October 1964.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#1a">4</a> Luca Cardelli and Rob Pike, “Squeak: a Language for Communicating with Mice,” <em>Computer Graphics</em>, 19(3) (July 1985: SIGGRAPH &lsquo;85 Proceedings), 199-204.</p>

<p>Rob Pike, “Newsqueak: a Language for Communicating with Mice,” <em>Computing Science Technical Report 143</em>, AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories, Murray Hill, 1989.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#2">7</a> Phil Winterbottom, “Alef Language Reference Manual,” in <em>Plan 9 Programmer&rsquo;s Manual: Volume Two</em>, AT&amp;T, Murray Hill, 1995.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#3">8</a> Bob Flandrena, “Alef Users&rsquo; Guide,” in <em>Plan 9 Programmer&rsquo;s Manual: Volume Two</em>, AT&amp;T, Murray Hill, 1995.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#14">9</a> Dennis M. Ritchie, “The Limbo Programming Language,”<a href="http://www.vitanuova.com/inferno/papers/limbo.html">38</a> in <em>Inferno Programmer&rsquo;s Manual, Volume 2</em>, Vita Nuova Holdings Ltd., York, 2000.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#4">10</a> M. Douglas McIlroy, “Squinting at Power Series,” <em>Software&ndash;Practice and Experience</em>, 20(7) (July 1990), 661-683.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#5">11</a> Rob Pike, “A Concurrent Window System,” <em>Computing Systems</em>, 2(2) 133-153.</p>

<p>Rob Pike, “Acme: A User Interface for Programmers,”<a href="http://plan9.bell-labs.com/sys/doc/acme.html">41</a> <em>Proceedings of the Winter 1994 USENIX Conference</em>, 223-234.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#7">13</a> golang.org, “The Go Programming Language”<a href="http://golang.org/">22</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#8">14</a> Gerard Holzmann, “Spin&rsquo;s Roots”<a href="http://spinroot.com/spin/Doc/roots.html">42</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://swtch.com#9">15</a> Gerard Holzmann, “Promela Language Reference”<a href="http://spinroot.com/spin/Man/promela.html">43</a>.</p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Treaps: The Magical Awesome BBT]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/11/25/treaps-the-magical-balanced-binary-tree/"/>
	    <updated>2013-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/11/25/treaps-the-magical-balanced-binary-tree/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://pavpanchekha.com/blog/treap.html" title="Permalink to Treaps: The Magical Awesome BBT" target="_blank">original document</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/treap_the_bbt.jpg" alt="Tree" title="Balanced Binary Tree" />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by Pavel Panchekha - September 1, 2011</h2>

<p>When you are about to use a Hash table, a map&hellip; consider using a BBT instead: ordering is embbedded and retrieving values will be faster on large sets.</p>

<hr />

<h1>Treaps: The Magical Awesome BBT</h1>

<h2>Table of Contents</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="#1">Binary Trees</a></li>
<li><a href="#2">Heaps</a></li>
<li><a href="#3">Our Goals</a></li>
<li><a href="#4">Theoretical Backing</a></li>
<li><a href="#5">Implementation</a>

<ul>
<li><a href="#6">Lookup and Containment</a></li>
<li><a href="#7">Insertion</a></li>
<li><a href="#8">Split &amp; Merge</a></li>
<li><a href="#9">Deletion</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="#10">Usage</a></li>
<li><a href="#11">A Quick Problem</a></li>
<li><a href="#12">Wrapping Up</a></li>
<li><a href="#13">Acknowledments</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Treaps are an awesome variant of balanced binary tree. By making some use of randomness, we have a BBT that is expected to be of logarithmic height, but is also easy to code, requiring none of the special-case bashing that characterizes red-black trees. Here, we&rsquo;ll code up a complete treap implementation in Lisp (particularly, pylisp) that is also fully functional.</p>

<h2><a name='1'>Binary Trees</a></h2>

<h6>Note</h6>

<hr />

<p>What I&rsquo;m calling a &ldquo;binary tree&rdquo; here is normally called a binary search tree. In true Lisp fashion, I&rsquo;m cutting out the unnecessary word &ldquo;search&rdquo; for now — we&rsquo;ll never have the occasion to discuss standard binary trees.</p>

<hr />

<p>Quick review: what&rsquo;s a &ldquo;binary tree&rdquo;? Simply put, it&rsquo;s a tree where each node has both a key and a value, and for each node, the left child has a smaller key and the right child has a larger key (we specifically avoid the case of non-unique keys, because we&rsquo;ll be discussing BBTs as a way of simulating maps). Recursing, we can see that the left subtree of any node has only nodes with smaller keys, and the right subtree of any node has only nodes with larger keys. This enables fast lookups for any key: in effect, we binary search the values. Of course, this only works if the left and right subtrees of all the nodes we pass are approximately equal in size. Now, how do we guarantee that? Well, that&rsquo;s the great problem of &ldquo;balancing&rdquo; a binary tree.</p>

<p>There exist many, many algorithms to balance binary trees, but most of them are absolutely horrible, horrible things with thousands of special cases. Which is a pity, really, as binary trees lend themselves to functional code very well, unlike, say, hash tables, which cannot be copied in part. There are further benefits to balanced binary trees. For example, say you&rsquo;re writing an address book, and you need to store key-value pairs of contacts and phone numbers. A naive programmer would use a hash table, but this is incorrect. After all, you only ever display the names in order, and thus by storing the contacts as a binary tree, you transform (O(n \log n)) code (because of the sort) into (O(n)) code (just the iteration). The ability to send small updates as opposed to complete new hash tables is another advantage of balanced binary trees. And it is for this reason that we embark on our epic journey to balance binary trees using treaps.</p>

<p>One crucial operation on binary trees is rotation. What this does is modify the tree in such a way as to preserve the order properties of the key.</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/treap-the-bbt/rotations.png" alt="Rotations" title="Rotations in BBT." />
</p>

<hr />

<p>Left and right rotation in a binary search tree</p>

<p>In the above picture, I&rsquo;m not actually drawing subtrees that don&rsquo;t matter — the greek letters represent full trees that we just preserve while rotating. If you&rsquo;re confused about which subtree ends up going where, take a deep breath, or maybe a short nap, and start from the top. In any case, it should be clear by inspection that this transformation retains the tree&rsquo;s order properties, which is really its most important feature. Further, it provides a way to move nodes upward in the tree — just as <code>x</code> moves upward as a result of the transformation above, we could have another rotation to move it yet further and further, until it became the root of the tree. In fact, any two binary trees can be transformed into each other using only tree rotations (assuming of course that they have the same number of elements). I should note that going left to right in the above diagram is called a right rotation, whereas right to left is called a left rotation.</p>

<h2><a name='2'>Heaps</a></h2>

<p>And now our second fundamental data structure that we will build upon: the &ldquo;heap&rdquo;. A heap is a very special-purpose data structure, often used to implement priority queues. The rule is simple: every node has a priority, and the priority of any node is less than those of its two children. And, working recursively, we see that any node has the lowest priority of its subtree.</p>

<h6>Note</h6>

<hr />

<p>Technically, what I&rsquo;ve described can be properly called a &ldquo;min-heap&rdquo;, because the root is the minimum element. Alternatively, one can make each node larger than its children, creating a &ldquo;max-heap&rdquo;. Normally, one does not actually care which a heap is, since the main property is that the root is extremal.</p>

<hr />

<h2><a name='3'>Our Goals</a></h2>

<p>Our goal is to create a treap implementation. We&rsquo;ll be using Lisp, in particular pylisp; feel free to follow along in whatever language you want. Our treap will support the following interface:</p>

<p><code>(get key treap)</code>
    Get the value associated with <code>key</code> from our treap.
<code>(set key val treap)</code>
    Return a new treap, which is the same as the old one except associates <code>key</code> with <code>val</code>.
<code>(del key treap)</code>
    Return a new treap, which is the same as the old except does not associate anything with <code>key</code>.
<code>(in key treap)</code>
    Return <code>#t</code> if <code>key</code> is in your treap, and <code>#f</code> if not.
<code>(merge left right)</code>
    <code>left</code> and <code>right</code> are proper treaps; all elements of <code>left</code> are lesser in key than any element of <code>right</code>, and vice-versa. Return the treap that contains all the elements from either <code>left</code> or <code>right</code>.
<code>(split key treap)</code>
    Return two treaps, one for all nodes with key less than <code>key</code>, and one for all nodes with larger keys. We assume that the treap does not contain <code>key</code>.
<code>(treap-&amp;gt;list treap)</code>
    Creates a nested list with format <code>(key left-child right-child)</code>.</p>

<p>Note that since our treap will be fully functional, <code>set</code>, <code>del</code>, and <code>merge</code> will return new treaps with the necessary modifications made; furthermore, we will require that each of these methods, with the exception of <code>treap-&amp;gt;list</code>, run in (O(\log n)) time.</p>

<h2><a name='4'>Theoretical Backing</a></h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ll define a treap as a sort of cross-polination between a binary tree and a heap. In particular, each node will have a <code>key</code>, a <code>val</code>, and a priority <code>p</code>, as well as a left child <code>left</code> and a right child <code>right</code> (both of which may be <code>#0</code>, that is, null). We will require that our treap is a binary tree in terms of its keys and values, but a heap in terms of its priorities. Balancing will be achieved by assigning the priorities at random; we hope that this will tend to move middling values into the root of the tree. We&rsquo;ll prove this result — that we expect the height of the treap to be logarithmic — later. For cleanness of code, we&rsquo;ll further require that the priorities and keys be unique.</p>

<p>Now, first, does there always exist a treap for a given set of keys and priorities? And, can we be sure that this treap is unique? A simple argument answers both in the positive. Clearly, the root node must be the node with lowest priority. This partitions the remaining nodes into two sets: those with key less than the root, and those with key greater. We recurse onto each of these sets, using as our base case the treap with a single node (clearly, it is unique).</p>

<p>Alright, fine; what about proving that we&rsquo;ll get logarithmic height? Well, let&rsquo;s make the assumption that our random keys are being drawn from a uniform distribution. Now consider the root node, and ask: what&rsquo;s the size of the larger of its children, relative to the total tree size? Well, let&rsquo;s say without loss of generality that the right subtree is the larger one. Consider the probability that this child is less than three quarters of the whole tree. What&rsquo;s the probability of this? One half (verify). So, we expect that for every two levels, our largest subtree must shrink by a factor of four thirds. But wait, this means that our tree is shrinking geometrically! So, we have a logarithmic bound. And that means that we win, and have a good, balanced binary tree.</p>

<h2><a name='5'>Implementation</a></h2>

<p>Alright, so we&rsquo;ve got our theory down pat, and it&rsquo;s time to start firing our massive s-expression-spewing assault rifles. First things first, we have to define our nodes:</p>

<pre><code>(class::simple Node (p key val left right))
</code></pre>

<p>For those of you unfamiliar with pylisp, this will define a class with fields <code>p</code>, <code>key</code>, and so on, and provide a basic constructor for this class.</p>

<p>How might we transform this <code>Node</code> into a nice list? Well, nothing to it!</p>

<pre><code>(def treap-&amp;gt;list (root)
  (if (is root Node)
    `(,root.key ,(treap-&amp;gt;list root.left) ,(treap-&amp;gt;list root.right))
    root))
</code></pre>

<p>Pylisp note: the <code>is</code> method checks if an object is an instance of a certain class, here used to bottom out our recursion.</p>

<p>Since they will be useful, let&rsquo;s also implement left and right rotations:</p>

<pre><code>(def left-rotate (node)
  (Node node.left.p node.left.key node.left.val
    node.left.left
    (Node node.p node.key node.val node.left.right node.right)))

(def right-rotate (node)
  (Node node.right.p node.right.key node.right.val
    (Node node.p node.key node.val node.left node.right.left)
    node.right.right))
</code></pre>

<h3><a name='6'>Lookup and Containment</a></h3>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s get cracking. First up is lookup, that is, the <code>get</code> function. Simple enough. Since our treap is already a binary tree, we can use the standard binary tree lookup algorithm, completely ignoring priorities:</p>

<pre><code>(def get (key root)
  (cond
    ((not root)
     (signal '(error not-found key get) key))
    ((&amp;lt; key root.key)
     (get key root.left))
    ((&amp;gt; key root.key)
     (get key root.right))
    ((= key root.key)
     root.val)))
</code></pre>

<p>Simple enough, eh? What about containment? Oh, it&rsquo;s even easier:</p>

<pre><code>(def in (key root)
  (cond
    ((not root)
     #f)
    ((&amp;lt; key root.key)
     (in key root.left))
    ((&amp;gt; key root.key)
     (in key root.right))
    ((= key root.key)
     #t)))
</code></pre>

<p>Alright, onward to mutation methods!</p>

<h3><a name='7'>Insertion</a></h3>

<p>Now on to the more difficult modification operations. How do we insert an element, how do we update a value? Well, we can spider down to the place we want to add the node very easily — it&rsquo;s the same as our <code>get</code> above. Now, we can just add the new node there, and if its priority is larger than its new parent&rsquo;s, we&rsquo;re golden. What if it&rsquo;s not? Well, then we have to move it upwards in the tree. How do we do that? Well, we mentioned how we move elements up and down before: it&rsquo;s called a tree rotation. So, all we have to do is, if our inserted element breaks the heap property of our treap, move it upwards by way of the appropriate rotation.</p>

<p>This is a complicated method, so let&rsquo;s do it step-by-step. First, we&rsquo;ll need to import a module to get random numbers:</p>

<pre><code>(use random)
</code></pre>

<p>Next, recall that we&rsquo;ll be generating a priority for this new element upon insertion, and then passing it up and down the call stack as necessary. This may seem like a waste of code — why not generate it once we get to the leaves and are ready to generate our new node? The simple answer is, &ldquo;trust me on this one&rdquo;. Anyway, here&rsquo;s our skeletal <code>set</code>:</p>

<pre><code>(def set (key val root #:(p (random.randint 0 1000000000)))
  (cond
    ((not root)
     ?) ; Just generate the new node
    ((&amp;lt; key root.key)
     ?) ; Recurse leftwards, then do a left-rotation if necessary
    ((&amp;gt; key root.key)
     ?) ; Same as the ( key root.key)
 (let (new (Node root.p root.key root.val
         root.left
         (set key val root.right #:(p p))))
   (if (&amp;lt; new.right.p new.p)
     (right-rotate new)
     new)))
</code></pre>

<p>Putting it together, we have:</p>

<pre><code>(def set (key val root #:(p (random.randint 0 1000000000)))
  (cond
    ((not root)
     (Node p key val #0 #0))
    ((&amp;lt; key root.key)
     (let (new (Node root.p root.key root.val
        (set key val root.left #:(p p))
        root.right))
       (if (&amp;lt; new.left.p new.p)
     (left-rotate new)
     new)))
    ((&amp;gt; key root.key)
     (let (new (Node root.p root.key root.val
        root.left
        (set key val root.right #:(p p))))
       (if (&amp;lt; new.right.p new.p)
     (right-rotate new)
     new)))
    ((= key root.key)
     (Node root.p root.key val root.left root.right))))
</code></pre>

<p>Don&rsquo;t worry, this is by far the scariest method we&rsquo;ll see. And note that this is completely functional — note a single <code>set!</code> call was made. Doesn&rsquo;t recursion mix so well with functional programming? Yes it does. Especially when treaps get involved.</p>

<h3><a name='8'>Split &amp; Merge</a></h3>

<p>Before we tackle deletion, let&rsquo;s take a quick detour to splitting and merging. What splitting does it produces two treaps from one, a left treap and a right treap, where the left treap contains only values less than a given key and the right treap contains only values greater than a given key. We assume that the key is not in the treap (otherwise, where would it go?). Of course, the left and right treaps that result from the splitting must themselves be valid treaps.</p>

<p>How are we going to do this? Well, we&rsquo;re gonna cheat. We&rsquo;re gonna add in a new node, with the given key, but give it a really low priority so that it becomes the root. Then we can just pluck off left and right subtreaps and return those. Nice and simple, huh?</p>

<pre><code>(def split (key root)
  (let (ins (set key #0 root #:(p (- 1))))
    `(,ins.left ,ins.right)))
</code></pre>

<p>Nice and easy, there we go. We&rsquo;re inserting a node with priority <code>-1</code>, which is guaranteed to be the smallest priority (all other nodes have a positive priority from zero to a billion). And because insertion is functional, we never have to explicitly remove our dummy node.</p>

<p>Now, what about merging? Merging takes two treaps that might have been the result of a <code>split</code>, and merges them into one treap. How? Well, given the two treaps, one can easily find the root element of the new treap — it&rsquo;s the root of one of the two treaps. Now, we have our root (say it came from the right tree), and we have its right child — that&rsquo;s just its original right child. After all, that right child already contains all of the larger elements, by definition. What about its left child? Well, we still have two treaps worth of elements to consider: the original left child of our new root, and the original left treap. And so we merge <strong>those</strong>, recursively.</p>

<pre><code>(def merge (left right)
  (cond
    ((not left)
     right)
    ((not right)
     left)
    ((&amp;lt; left.p right.p)
     (Node left.p  left.key  left.val  left.left (merge left.right right)))
    (#t
     (Node right.p right.key right.val (merge right.left left) right.right))))
</code></pre>

<p>What&rsquo;s that <code>#t</code> doing there? Well, that&rsquo;s the default clause in my conditional, you might say. The reason it isn&rsquo;t <code>(&amp;gt; left.p right.p)</code> is to guard against the minute chance of non-unique priorities.</p>

<h6>Note</h6>

<hr />

<p>The first time I wrote this, there were errors. They are now fixed. The new code is deceptively similar; but then again, even minor changes are crucial in recursive functions (since those errors propogate).</p>

<hr />

<h3><a name='9'>Deletion</a></h3>

<p>Alright. You might say, this treap stuff seems okay so far, but so do red-black trees, and then you hit deletion. As you&rsquo;re about to see, deletion for treaps is very nice and intuitive. <strong>Intuitive</strong>. That&rsquo;s right. Onward!</p>

<p>Now, consider the node you want to delete. If your node is a leaf node, your job is easy — just delete it. If your node has only one child, your job is also pretty easy — just remove the node and connect its single child in its place. But what if the node has two children? Then, when you remove it, you have to somehow combine two the two child subtreaps into one. But <strong>how</strong>? How might we do such a merger?</p>

<p>Oh, yeah, <code>merge</code>.</p>

<p>The rest of the method is a simple recursion back and forth:</p>

<pre><code>(def del (key root)
  (cond
    ((not root)
     (signal '(error not-found key del) key))
    ((&amp;lt; key root.key)
     (Node root.p root.key root.val (del key root.left) root.right))
    ((&amp;gt; key root.key)
     (Node root.p root.key root.val root.left (del key root.right)))
    ((= key root.key)
     (merge root.left root.right))))
</code></pre>

<p>Note the pure, happy simplicity of this method! Oh, the joys of treaps!</p>

<h2><a name='10'>Usage</a></h2>

<p>I like to add some basic tester code to the bottom of my files. Not exhaustive unit tests, mind, you (we don&rsquo;t want import taking forever, do we?), but some basic usage, just to make sure everything works. Let&rsquo;s do that here:</p>

<pre><code>(use tester)

(test &quot;Sanity check&quot;
  (let (treap #0)
    (set! treap (set 5 'a treap))
    (set! treap (set 7 'b treap))
    (assert (= (get 5 treap) 'a))
    (assert (= (get 7 treap) 'b))
    (set! treap (set 2 'c treap))
    (assert (= (get 2 treap) 'c))
    (set! treap (set 2 'd treap))
    (assert (= (get 2 treap) 'd))
    (set! treap (del 5 treap))
    (assert (not (in 5 treap)))))

(test &quot;Fairly Balanced&quot;
  (let (treap #0)
    (signal '(warning test slow-test) &quot;Balancing test&quot;)
    (for (i (range 1000))
      (set! treap (set i #0 treap))
      (print i))
    (assert (&amp;lt; (depth treap) 40))))
</code></pre>

<h2><a name='11'>A Quick Problem</a></h2>

<p>Suppose we want to create a sorted array; that is, we want to be able to retrieve the (n)-th largest key, in (O(\log n)) time. How do we do this? There is a rather simple way, involving treaps (or, really, any balanced binary tree). As a hint, I suggest considering the fact that we&rsquo;re not using the value stored in each node for anything, thus leaving it open to be appropriated for some purpose.</p>

<h2><a name='12'>Wrapping Up</a></h2>

<p>Overall, the code above weighs in at under 100 lines, and that&rsquo;s including the tester code. Perhaps that&rsquo;s not impressive. If it isn&rsquo;t, go write red-black trees in Java. We&rsquo;ll see who&rsquo;s laughing then.</p>

<p>What about cool optimizations? Anything in that department? Well, it&rsquo;s a good thing you ask. Because, you see, we&rsquo;ve got all of these priorities floating around. And of course they&rsquo;re supposed to be random. But don&rsquo;t you just get the urge to fiddle with them?</p>

<p>One simple optimization is to decrease the priority of a node every time it is accessed (whether by <code>get</code> or <code>set</code>). This will slowly migrate your commonly-accessed nodes up to the top of the treap, where they&rsquo;re faster to get at. Of course, this might make accesses slower, as you need to rewrite the treap. Your mileage may vary. Look before you leap, benchmark when in doubt, beware of dog.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not providing code for this variant. Because in my experience, on pylisp, this behavior is rarely what you want, unless of course you have a treap of several thousand elements but you only ever access three of them. In which case you need a better brain, not a better algorithm. But I&rsquo;ll leave this optimization as an exercise to the reader. As a hint, I&rsquo;d suggest going over your code for <code>split</code> carefully if you do optimize this, and also make sure to deal with the case where priorities are non-unique.</p>

<h3><a name='13'>Acknowledgments</a></h3>

<p>Thanks to Sam Fingeret for first introducing me to treaps, and for helping out with the details of the proof that the height is expected to be logarithmic. Thank you as well to Mark Velednitsky for editing this writeup, even though he can&rsquo;t stand the sight of Lisp.</p>

<p>Thanks also to folks on Hacker News who provided a lively discussion.</p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I&#39;d like to see on front pages of newspapers.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/10/24/what-we-would-like-to-read-in-media/"/>
	    <updated>2013-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/10/24/what-we-would-like-to-read-in-media/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/opinion/noam-chomsky-what-id-like-to-see-on-front-pages-of-newspapers-29654898.html" target="_blank">original document</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/Incal.jpg" alt="Capitalism" title="The name of what the present is." />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by Noam Chomsky - October 12th, 2013</h2>

<hr />

<p>Another splendid,and horrendous, synthesis about our present and its a-coming near future.</p>

<pre><code>RECD: &quot;really existing capitalist democracy&quot;,
RECD for short, pronounced &quot;wrecked&quot; by accident.
</code></pre>

<hr />

<p>In these comments I&rsquo;ll focus primarily on the United States for several reasons: One, it&rsquo;s the most important country in terms of its power and influence. Second, it&rsquo;s the most advanced - not in its inherent character, but in the sense that because of its power, other societies tend to move in that direction.</p>

<p>The third reason is just that I know it better. But I think what I say generalises much more widely - at least to my knowledge, obviously there are some variations. So I&rsquo;ll be concerned then with tendencies in American society and what they portend for the world, given American power.</p>

<p>American power is diminishing, as it has been in fact since its peak in 1945, but it&rsquo;s still incomparable. And it&rsquo;s dangerous. Obama&rsquo;s remarkable global terror campaign and the limited, pathetic reaction to it in the West is one shocking example. And it is a campaign of international terrorism - by far the most extreme in the world. Those who harbour any doubts on that should read the report issued by Stanford University and New York University, and actually I&rsquo;ll return to even more serious examples than international terrorism.</p>

<p>According to received doctrine, we live in capitalist democracies, which are the best possible system, despite some flaws. There&rsquo;s been an interesting debate over the years about the relation between capitalism and democracy, for example, are they even compatible? I won&rsquo;t be pursuing this because I&rsquo;d like to discuss a different system - what we could call the &ldquo;really existing capitalist democracy&rdquo;, RECD for short, pronounced &ldquo;wrecked&rdquo; by accident. To begin with, how does RECD compare with democracy? Well that depends on what we mean by &ldquo;democracy&rdquo;.</p>

<p>There are several versions of this. One, there is a kind of received version. It&rsquo;s soaring rhetoric of the Obama variety, patriotic speeches, what children are taught in school, and so on. In the U.S. version, it&rsquo;s government &ldquo;of, by and for the people&rdquo;. And it&rsquo;s quite easy to compare that with RECD.</p>

<p>In the United States, one of the main topics of academic political science is the study of attitudes and policy and their correlation. The study of attitudes is reasonably easy in the United States: heavily-polled society, pretty serious and accurate polls, and policy you can see, and you can compare them. And the results are interesting. In the work that&rsquo;s essentially the gold standard in the field, it&rsquo;s concluded that for roughly 70% of the population - the lower 70% on the wealth/income scale - they have no influence on policy whatsoever. They&rsquo;re effectively disenfranchised.</p>

<p>As you move up the wealth/income ladder, you get a little bit more influence on policy. When you get to the top, which is maybe a tenth of one percent, people essentially get what they want, i.e. they determine the policy. So the proper term for that is not democracy; it&rsquo;s plutocracy.</p>

<p>Inquiries of this kind turn out to be dangerous stuff because they can tell people too much about the nature of the society in which they live. So fortunately, Congress has banned funding for them, so we won&rsquo;t have to worry about them in the future.</p>

<p>These characteristics of RECD show up all the time. So the major domestic issue in the United States for the public is jobs. Polls show that very clearly. For the very wealthy and the financial institutions, the major issue is the deficit. Well, what about policy? There&rsquo;s now a sequester in the United States, a sharp cutback in funds. Is that because of jobs or is it because of the deficit? Well, the deficit.</p>

<p>Europe, incidentally, is much worse - so outlandish that even The Wall Street Journal has been appalled by the disappearance of democracy in Europe. A couple of weeks ago it had an article which concluded that &ldquo;the French, the Spanish, the Irish, the Dutch, Portuguese, Greeks, Slovenians, Slovakians and Cypriots have to varying degrees voted against the currency bloc&rsquo;s economic model since the crisis began three years ago. Yet economic policies have changed little in response to one electoral defeat after another. The left has replaced the right; the right has ousted the left.</p>

<p>Even the centre-right trounced Communists (in Cyprus) - but the economic policies have essentially remained the same: governments will continue to cut spending and raise taxes.&rdquo; It doesn&rsquo;t matter what people think and &ldquo;national governments must follow macro-economic directives set by the European Commission&rdquo;. Elections are close to meaningless, very much as in Third World countries that are ruled by the international financial institutions. That&rsquo;s what Europe has chosen to become. It doesn&rsquo;t have to.</p>

<p>Returning to the United States, where the situation is not quite that bad, there&rsquo;s the same disparity between public opinion and policy on a very wide range of issues. Take for example the issue of minimum wage. The one view is that the minimum wage ought to be indexed to the cost of living and high enough to prevent falling below the poverty line.</p>

<p>Eighty percent of the public support that and forty percent of the wealthy. What&rsquo;s the minimum wage? Going down, way below these levels. It&rsquo;s the same with laws that facilitate union activity: strongly supported by the public; opposed by the very wealthy - disappearing.</p>

<p>The same is true on national healthcare. The U.S., as you may know, has a health system which is an international scandal, it has twice the per capita costs of other OECD countries and relatively poor outcomes. The only privatised, pretty much unregulated system.</p>

<p>The public doesn&rsquo;t like it. They&rsquo;ve been calling for national healthcare, public options, for years, but the financial institutions think it&rsquo;s fine, so it stays: stasis. In fact, if the United States had a healthcare system like comparable countries there wouldn&rsquo;t be any deficit. The famous deficit would be erased, which doesn&rsquo;t matter that much anyway.</p>

<p>One of the most interesting cases has to do with taxes. For 35 years there have been polls on &lsquo;what do you think taxes ought to be?&rsquo; Large majorities have held that the corporations and the wealthy should pay higher taxes. They&rsquo;ve steadily been going down through this period.</p>

<p>On and on, the policy throughout is almost the opposite of public opinion, which is a typical property of RECD.</p>

<p>In the past, the United States has sometimes, kind of sardonically, been described as a one-party state: the business party with two factions called Democrats and Republicans. That&rsquo;s no longer true. It&rsquo;s still a one-party state, the business party. But it only has one faction. The faction is moderate Republicans, who are now called Democrats.</p>

<p>There are virtually no moderate Republicans in what&rsquo;s called the Republican Party and virtually no liberal Democrats in what&rsquo;s called the Democratic [sic] Party. It&rsquo;s basically a party of what would be moderate Republicans and similarly, Richard Nixon would be way at the left of the political spectrum today. Eisenhower would be in outer space.</p>

<p>There is still something called the Republican Party, but it long ago abandoned any pretence of being a normal parliamentary party. It&rsquo;s in lock-step service to the very rich and the corporate sector and has a catechism that everyone has to chant in unison, kind of like the old Communist Party.</p>

<p>The distinguished conservative commentator, one of the most respected - Norman Ornstein - describes today&rsquo;s Republican Party as, in his words, &ldquo;a radical insurgency - ideologically extreme, scornful of facts and compromise, dismissive of its political opposition&rdquo; - a serious danger to the society, as he points out.</p>

<p>In short, Really Existing Capitalist Democracy is very remote from the soaring rhetoric about democracy. But there is another version of democracy. Actually it&rsquo;s the standard doctrine of progressive, contemporary democratic theory. So I&rsquo;ll give some illustrative quotes from leading figures - incidentally not figures on the right. These are all good Woodrow Wilson-FDR-Kennedy liberals, mainstream ones in fact.</p>

<p>So according to this version of democracy, &ldquo;the public are ignorant and meddlesome outsiders. They have to be put in their place. Decisions must be in the hands of an intelligent minority of responsible men, who have to be protected from the trampling and roar of the bewildered herd&rdquo;. The herd has a function, as it&rsquo;s called.</p>

<p>They&rsquo;re supposed to lend their weight every few years, to a choice among the responsible men. But apart from that, their function is to be &ldquo;spectators, not participants in action&rdquo; - and it&rsquo;s for their own good. Because as the founder of liberal political science pointed out, we should not succumb to “democratic dogmatisms about people being the best judges of their own interest&rdquo;. They&rsquo;re not. We&rsquo;re the best judges, so it would be irresponsible to let them make choices just as it would be irresponsible to let a three-year-old run into the street. Attitudes and opinions therefore have to be controlled for the benefit of those you are controlling. It&rsquo;s necessary to &ldquo;regiment their minds&rdquo;. It&rsquo;s necessary also to discipline the institutions responsible for the &ldquo;indoctrination of the young.&rdquo; All quotes, incidentally.</p>

<p>And if we can do this, we might be able to get back to the good old days when “Truman had been able to govern the country with the cooperation of a relatively small number of Wall Street lawyers and bankers.&rdquo; This is all from icons of the liberal establishment, the leading progressive democratic theorists. Some of you may recognise some of the quotes.</p>

<p>The roots of these attitudes go back quite far. They go back to the first stirrings of modern democracy. The first were in England in the 17th Century. As you know, later in the United States. And they persist in fundamental ways. The first democratic revolution was England in the 1640s. There was a civil war between king and parliament. But the gentry, the people who called themselves &ldquo;the men of best quality&rdquo;, were appalled by the rising popular forces that were beginning to appear on the public arena.</p>

<p>They didn&rsquo;t want to support either king or parliament. Quote their pamphlets, they didn&rsquo;t want to be ruled by &ldquo;knights and gentlemen, who do but oppress us, but we want to be governed by countrymen like ourselves, who know the people&rsquo;s sores&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s a pretty terrifying sight. Now the rabble has been a pretty terrifying sight ever since. Actually it was long before.</p>

<p>It remained so a century after the British democratic revolution. The founders of the American republic had pretty much the same view about the rabble. So they determined that &ldquo;power must be in the hands of the wealth of the nation, the more responsible set of men. Those who have sympathy for property owners and their rights&rdquo;, and of course for slave owners at the time. In general, men who understand that a fundamental task of government is “to protect the minority of the opulent from the majority&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Those are quotes from James Madison, the main framer - this was in the Constitutional Convention, which is much more revealing than the Federalist Papers which people read. The Federalist Papers were basically a propaganda effort to try to get the public to go along with the system. But the debates in the Constitutional Convention are much more revealing. And in fact the constitutional system was created on that basis.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have time to go through it, but it basically adhered to the principle which was enunciated simply by John Jay, the president of the ­ Continental Congress, then first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, and as he put it, &ldquo;those who own the country ought to govern it&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s the primary doctrine of RECD to the present.</p>

<p>There have been many popular struggles since - and they&rsquo;ve won many victories. The masters, however, do not relent. The more freedom is won, the more intense are the efforts to redirect the society to a proper course. And the 20th Century progressive democratic theory that I&rsquo;ve just sampled is not very different from the RECD that has been achieved, apart from the question of: Which responsible men should rule? Should it be bankers or intellectual elites? Or for that matter should it be the Central Committee in a different version of similar doctrines?</p>

<p>Well, another important feature of RECD is that the public must be kept in the dark about what is happening to them. The &ldquo;herd&rdquo; must remain &ldquo;bewildered&rdquo;. The reasons were explained lucidly by the professor of the science of government at Harvard - that&rsquo;s the official name - another respected liberal figure, Samuel Huntington. As he pointed out, &ldquo;power remains strong when it remains in the dark. Exposed to sunlight, it begins to evaporate&rdquo;. Bradley Manning is facing a life in prison for failure to comprehend this scientific principle. Now Edward Snowden as well.</p>

<p>And it works pretty well. If you take a look at polls, it reveals how well it works. So for example, recent polls pretty consistently reveal that Republicans are preferred to Democrats on most issues and crucially on the issues in which the public opposes the policies of the Republicans and favours the policies of the Democrats.</p>

<p>One striking example of this is that majorities say that they favour the Republicans on tax policy, while the same majorities oppose those policies. This runs across the board. This is even true of the far right, the Tea Party types. This goes along with an astonishing level of contempt for government. Favourable opinions about Congress are literally in the single digits. The rest of the government as well. It&rsquo;s all declining sharply.</p>

<p>Results such as these, which are pretty consistent, illustrate demoralisation of the public of a kind that&rsquo;s unusual, although there are examples - the late Weimar Republic comes to mind. The tasks of ensuring that the rabble keep to their function as bewildered spectators, takes many forms. The simplest form is simply to restrict entry into the political system. Iran just had an election, as you know. And it was rightly criticised on the grounds that even to participate, you had to be vetted by the guardian council of clerics. In the United States, you don&rsquo;t have to be vetted by clerics, but rather you have to be vetted by concentrations of private capital. Unless you pass their filter, you don&rsquo;t enter the political system - with very rare exceptions.</p>

<p>There are many mechanisms, too familiar to review, but that&rsquo;s not safe enough either. There are major institutions that are specifically dedicated to undermining authentic democracy. One of them is called the public relations industry. A huge industry, it was in fact developed on the principle that it&rsquo;s necessary to regiment the minds of men, much as an army regiments its soldiers - I was actually quoting from one of its leading figures before.</p>

<p>The role of the PR industry in elections is explicitly to undermine the school-child version of democracy. What you learn in school is that democracies are based on informed voters making rational decisions. All you have to do is take a look at an electoral campaign run by the PR industry and see that the purpose is to create uninformed voters who will make irrational decisions. For the PR industry that&rsquo;s a very easy transition from their primary function.</p>

<p>Their primary function is commercial advertising. Commercial advertising is designed to undermine markets. If you took an economics course you learned that markets are based on informed consumers making rational choices. If you turn on the TV set, you see that ads are designed to create irrational, uninformed consumers making irrational choices. The whole purpose is to undermine markets in the technical sense.</p>

<p>They&rsquo;re well aware of it, incidentally. So for example, after Obama&rsquo;s election in 2008, a couple of months later the advertising industry had its annual conference. Every year they award a prize for the best marketing campaign of the year. That year they awarded it to Obama.</p>

<p>He beat out Apple computer, did an even better job of deluding the public - or his PR agents did. If you want to hear some of it, turn on the television today and listen to the soaring rhetoric at the G-8 Summit in Belfast. It&rsquo;s standard.</p>

<p>There was interesting commentary on this in the business press, primarily The London Financial Times, which had a long article, interviewing executives about what they thought about the election. And they were quite euphoric about this. They said this gives them a new model for how to delude the public. The Obama model could replace the Reagan model, which worked pretty well for a while.</p>

<p>Turning to the economy, the core of the economy today is financial institutions. They&rsquo;ve vastly expanded since the 1970s, along with a parallel development - accelerated shift of production abroad. There have also been critical changes in the character of financial institutions.</p>

<p>If you go back to the 1960s, banks were banks. If you had some money, you put it in the bank to lend it to somebody to buy a house or start a business, or whatever. Now that&rsquo;s a very marginal aspect of financial institutions today.</p>

<p>They&rsquo;re mostly devoted to intricate, exotic manipulations with markets. And they&rsquo;re huge. In the United States, financial institutions, big banks mostly, had 40% of corporate profit in 2007. That was on the eve of the financial crisis, for which they were largely responsible. After the crisis, a number of professional economists - Nobel laureate Robert Solow, Harvard&rsquo;s Benjamin Friedman - wrote articles in which they pointed out that economists haven&rsquo;t done much study of the impact of the financial institutions on the economy.</p>

<p>Which is kind of remarkable, considering its scale. But after the crisis they took a look and they both concluded that probably the impact of the financial institutions on the economy is negative. Actually there are some who are much more outspoken than that. The most respected financial correspondent in the English-speaking world is Martin Wolf of the Financial Times. He writes that the &ldquo;out-of-control financial sector is eating out the modern market economy from the inside, just as the larva of the spider wasp eats out the host in which it has been laid&rdquo;. By &ldquo;the market economy&rdquo; he means the productive economy.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a recent issue of the main business weekly, Bloomberg Business Week, which reported a study of the IMF that found that the largest banks make no profit. What they earn, according to the IMF analysis, traces to the government insurance policy, the so-called too-big-to-fail policy.</p>

<p>There is a widely publicised bailout, but that&rsquo;s the least of it. There&rsquo;s a whole series of other devices by which the government insurance policy aids the big banks: cheap credit and many other things. And according to the IMF at least, that&rsquo;s the totality of their profit. The editors of the journal say this is crucial to understanding why the big banks present such a threat to the global economy - and to the people of the country, of course.</p>

<p>After the crash, there was the first serious attention by professional economists to what&rsquo;s called systemic risk. They knew it existed but it wasn&rsquo;t much a topic of investigation. &lsquo;Systemic risk&rsquo; means the risk that if a transaction fails, the whole system may collapse.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s called an externality in economic theory. It&rsquo;s a footnote. And it’s one of the fundamental flaws of market systems, a well-known, inherent flaw, is externalities. Every transaction has impacts on others which just aren&rsquo;t taken into account in a market transaction. Systemic risk is a big one. And there are much more serious illustrations than that. I&rsquo;ll come back to it.</p>

<p>What about the productive economy under RECD? Here there&rsquo;s a mantra too. The mantra is based on entrepreneurial initiative and consumer choice in a free market. There are agreements established called free-trade agreements, which are based on the mantra. That&rsquo;s all mythology.</p>

<p>The reality is that there is massive state intervention in the productive economy and the free-trade agreements are anything but free-trade agreements. That should be obvious.</p>

<p>Just to take one example: The information technology (IT) revolution, which is driving the economy, that was based on decades of work in effectively the state sector - hard, costly, creative work substantially in the state sector, no consumer choice at all, there was entrepreneurial initiative but it was largely limited to getting government grants or bailouts or procurement.</p>

<p>Except by some economists, that&rsquo;s underestimated but a very significant factor in corporate profit. If you can&rsquo;t sell something, hand it over the government. They&rsquo;ll buy it.</p>

<p>After a long period - decades in fact - of hard, creative work, the primary research and development, the results are handed over to private enterprise for commercialisation and profit. That&rsquo;s Steve Jobs and Bill Gates and so on. It&rsquo;s not quite that simple of course. But that’s a core part of the picture. The system goes way back to the origins of industrial economies, but it&rsquo;s dramatically true since WWII that this ought to be the core of the study of the productive economy.</p>

<p>Another central aspect of RECD is concentration of capital. In just the past 20 years in the United States, the share of profits of the two hundred largest enterprises has very sharply risen, probably the impact of the Internet, it seems. These tendencies towards oligopoly also undermine the mantra, of course. Interesting topics but I won&rsquo;t pursue them any further.</p>

<p>Instead, I&rsquo;d like to turn to another question. What are the prospects for the future under RECD? There&rsquo;s an answer. They&rsquo;re pretty grim. It&rsquo;s no secret that there are a number of dark shadows that hover over every topic that we discuss and there are two that are particularly ominous, so I&rsquo;ll keep to those, though there are others. One is environmental catastrophe. The other is nuclear war. Both of which of course threaten the prospects for decent survival and not in the remote future.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t say very much about the first, environmental catastrophe. That should be obvious. Certainly the scale of the danger should be obvious to anyone with eyes open, anyone who is literate, particularly those who read scientific journals. Every issue of a technical journal virtually has more dire warnings than the last one.</p>

<p>There are various reactions to this around the world. There are some who seek to act decisively to prevent possible catastrophe. At the other extreme, major efforts are underway to accelerate the danger. Leading the effort to intensify the likely disaster is the richest and most powerful country in world history, with incomparable advantages and the most prominent example of RECD - the one that others are striving towards.</p>

<p>Leading the efforts to preserve conditions in which our immediate descendants might have a decent life, are the so-called &ldquo;primitive&rdquo; societies: First Nations in Canada, Aboriginal societies in Australia, tribal societies and others like them. The countries that have large and influential indigenous populations are well in the lead in the effort to &ldquo;defend the Earth&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s their phrase. The countries that have driven indigenous populations to extinction or extreme marginalisation are racing forward enthusiastically towards destruction. This is one of the major features of contemporary history.</p>

<p>One of those things that ought to be on front pages. So take Ecuador, which has a large indigenous population. It&rsquo;s seeking aid from the rich countries to allow it to keep its substantial hydrocarbon reserves underground, which is where they ought to be. Now meanwhile, the US and Canada are enthusiastically seeking to burn every drop of fossil fuel, including the most dangerous kind - Canadian tar sands - and to do so as quickly and fully as possible - without a side glance on what the world might look like after this extravagant commitment to self-destruction. Actually, every issue of the daily papers suffices to illustrate this lunacy. And lunacy is the right word for it. It&rsquo;s exactly the opposite of what rationality would demand, unless it&rsquo;s the skewed rationality of RECD.</p>

<p>Well, there have been massive corporate campaigns to implant and safeguard the lunacy. But despite them, there&rsquo;s still a real problem in American society. The public is still too committed to scientific rationality. One of the many divergences between policy and opinion is that the American public is close to the global norm in concern about the environment and calling for actions to prevent the catastrophe and that&rsquo;s a pretty high level. Meanwhile, bipartisan policy is dedicated to &lsquo;bringing it on&rsquo;, in a phrase that George W. Bush made famous in the case of Iraq.</p>

<p>Fortunately, the corporate sector is riding to the rescue to deal with this problem. There is a corporate funded organisation - the American Legislative Exchange Council (ALEC). It designs legislation for states. No need to comment on what kind of legislation. They&rsquo;ve got a lot of clout and money behind them. So the programs tend to get instituted.</p>

<p>Right now they&rsquo;re instituting a new program to try to overcome the excessive rationality of the public. It&rsquo;s a program of instruction for K-12 (kindergarten to 12th grade in schools). Its publicity says that the idea is to improve critical faculties - I&rsquo;d certainly be in favour of that - by balanced teaching.</p>

<p>&lsquo;Balanced teaching&rsquo; means that if a sixth grade class learned something about what&rsquo;s happening to the climate, they have to be presented with material on climate change denial so that they have balanced teaching and can develop their critical faculties. Maybe that&rsquo;ll help overcome the failure of massive corporate propaganda campaigns to make the population ignorant and irrational enough to safeguard short-term profit for the rich. It’s pointedly the goal and several states have already accepted it.</p>

<p>Well, it&rsquo;s worth remembering, without pursuing it that these are deep-seated institutional properties of RECD. They&rsquo;re not easy to uproot. All of this is apart from the institutional necessity to maximise short-term profit while ignoring an externality that&rsquo;s vastly more serious even than systemic risk.</p>

<p>For systemic risk, the market failure - the culprits - can run to the powerful nanny state that they foster with cap in hand and they&rsquo;ll be bailed out, as we&rsquo;ve just observed again and will in the future. In the case of destruction of the environment, the conditions for decent existence, there&rsquo;s no guardian angel around - nobody to run to with cap in hand. For that reason alone, the prospects for decent survival under RECD are quite dim.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s turn to the other shadow: nuclear war. It&rsquo;s a threat that&rsquo;s been with us for 70 years. It still is. In some ways it&rsquo;s growing. One of the reasons for it is that under RECD, the rights and needs of the general population are a minor matter. That extends to security. There is another prevailing mantra, particularly in the academic professions, claiming that governments seek to protect national security.</p>

<p>Anyone who has studied international relations theory has heard that. That&rsquo;s mostly mythology. The governments seek to extend power and domination and to benefit their primary domestic constituencies - in the US, primarily the corporate sector. The consequence is that security does not have a high priority. We see that all the time. Right now in fact.</p>

<p>Take say Obama&rsquo;s operation to murder Osama Bin Laden, prime suspect for the <sup>9</sup>&frasl;<sub>11</sub> attack. Obama made an important speech on national security last May 23rd. It was widely covered.</p>

<p>There was one crucial paragraph in the speech that was ignored in the coverage. Obama hailed the operation, took pride in it - an operation which incidentally is another step at dismantling the foundations of Anglo-American law, back to the Magna Carta, namely the presumption of innocence. But that&rsquo;s by now so familiar, it&rsquo;s not even necessary to talk about it. But there&rsquo;s more to it. Obama did hail the operation but he added to it that it &ldquo;cannot be the norm&rdquo;. The reason is that &ldquo;the risks were immense&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The Navy SEALs who carried out the murder might have been embroiled in an extended firefight, but even though by luck that didn&rsquo;t happen, &ldquo;the cost to our relationship with Pakistan - and the backlash of the Pakistani public over the encroachment on their territory&rdquo;, the aggression in other words, &ldquo;was so severe that we&rsquo;re just now beginning to rebuild this important partnership&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s more than that. Let&rsquo;s add a couple of details. The SEALs were under orders to fight their way out if they were apprehended. They would not have been left to their fate if they had been, in Obama&rsquo;s words, been &ldquo;embroiled in an extended firefight&rdquo;. The full force of the US military would have been employed to extricate them. Pakistan has a powerful military. It&rsquo;s well-trained, highly protective of state sovereignty. Of course, it has nuclear weapons. And leading Pakistani specialists on nuclear policy and issues are quite concerned by the exposure of the nuclear weapons system to jihadi elements.</p>

<p>It could have escalated to a nuclear war. And in fact it came pretty close. While the SEALs were still inside the Bin Laden compound, the Pakistani chief of staff, General Kayani, was informed of the invasion and he ordered his staff in his words to &ldquo;confront any unidentified aircraft&rdquo;. He assumed it was probably coming from India. Meanwhile in Kabul, General David Petraeus, head of the Central Command, ordered &ldquo;U.S. warplanes to respond if Pakistanis scrambled their fighter jets&rdquo;. It was that close. Going back to Obama, &ldquo;by luck&rdquo; it didn&rsquo;t happen. But the risk was faced without noticeable concern, without even reporting in fact.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot more to say about that operation and its immense cost to Pakistan, but instead of that let&rsquo;s look more closely at the concern for security more generally. Beginning with security from terror, and then turning to the much more important question of security from instant destruction by nuclear weapons.</p>

<p>As I mentioned, Obama&rsquo;s now conducting the world&rsquo;s greatest international terrorist campaign - the drones and special forces campaign. It&rsquo;s also a terror-generating campaign. The common understanding at the highest level [is] that these actions generate potential terrorists. I&rsquo;ll quote General Stanley McChrystal, Petraeus&rsquo; predecessor. He says that &ldquo;for every innocent person you kill&rdquo;, and there are plenty of them, &ldquo;you create ten new enemies&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Take the marathon bombing in Boston a couple of months ago, that you all read about. You probably didn&rsquo;t read about the fact that two days after the marathon bombing there was a drone bombing in Yemen. Usually we don&rsquo;t happen to hear much about drone bombings. They just go on - just straight terror operations which the media aren&rsquo;t interested in because we don&rsquo;t care about international terrorism as long as the victims are somebody else. But this one we happened to know about by accident.</p>

<p>There was a young man from the village that was attacked who was in the United States and he happened to testify before Congress. He testified about it. He said that for several years, the jihadi elements in Yemen had been trying to turn the village against Americans, get them to hate Americans. But the villagers didn&rsquo;t accept it because the only thing they knew about the United States was what he told them. And he liked the United States. So he was telling them it was a great place. So the jihadi efforts didn&rsquo;t work.</p>

<p>Then he said one drone attack has turned the entire village into people who hate America and want to destroy it. They killed a man who everybody knew and they could have easily apprehended if they&rsquo;d wanted. But in our international terror campaigns we don&rsquo;t worry about that and we don&rsquo;t worry about security.</p>

<p>One of the striking examples was the invasion of Iraq. U.S. and British intelligence agencies informed their governments that the invasion of Iraq was likely to lead to an increase in terrorism. They didn&rsquo;t care. In fact, it did. Terrorism increased by a factor of seven the first year after the Iraqi invasion, according to government statistics. Right now the government is defending the massive surveillance operation. That&rsquo;s on the front pages. The defence is on grounds that we have to do it to apprehend terrorists.</p>

<p>If there were a free press - an authentic free press - the headlines would be ridiculing this claim on the grounds that policy is designed in such a way that it amplifies the terrorist risk. But you can&rsquo;t find that, which is one of innumerable indications of how far we are from anything that might be called a free press.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s turn to the more serious problem: instant destruction by nuclear weapons. That&rsquo;s never been a high concern for state authorities. There are many striking examples. Actually, we know a lot about it because the United States is an unusually free and open society and there&rsquo;s plenty of internal documents that are released. So we can find out about it if we like.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s go back to 1950. In 1950, U.S. security was just overwhelming. There&rsquo;d never been anything like it in human history. There was one potential danger: ICBMs with hydrogen bomb warheads. They didn&rsquo;t exist, but they were going to exist sooner or later. The Russians knew that they were way behind in military technology. They offered the U.S. a treaty to ban the development of ICBMs with hydrogen bomb warheads. That would have been a terrific contribution to US security.</p>

<p>There is one major history of nuclear weapons policy written by McGeorge Bundy, National Security Advisor for Kennedy and Johnson. In his study he has a couple of casual sentences on this. He said that he was unable to find even a staff paper discussing this. Here&rsquo;s a possibility to save the country from total disaster and there wasn&rsquo;t even a paper discussing it. No one cared. Forget it, we&rsquo;ll go on to the important things.</p>

<p>A couple of years later, in 1952, Stalin made a public offer, which was pretty remarkable, to permit unification of Germany with internationally supervised free elections, in which the Communists would certainly lose, on one condition - that Germany be demilitarised. That&rsquo;s hardly a minor issue for the Russians. Germany alone had practically destroyed them several times in the century. Germany militarised and part of a hostile Western alliance is a major threat. That was the offer.</p>

<p>The offer was public. It also of course would have led to an end to the official reason for NATO. It was dismissed with ridicule. Couldn&rsquo;t be true. There were a few people who took it seriously - James Warburg, a respected international commentator, but he was just dismissed with ridicule. Today, scholars are looking back at it, especially with the Russian archives opening up. And they&rsquo;re discovering that in fact it was apparently serious. But nobody could pay attention to it because it didn&rsquo;t accord with policy imperatives - vast production of threat of war.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s go on a couple of years to the late &lsquo;50s, when Khrushchev took over. He realised that Russia was way behind economically and that it could not compete with the United States in military technology and hope to carry out economic development, which he was hoping to do. So he offered a sharp mutual cutback in offensive weapons.</p>

<p>The Eisenhower administration kind of dismissed it. The Kennedy administration listened. They considered the possibility and they rejected it. Khrushchev went on to introduce a sharp unilateral reduction of offensive weapons. The Kennedy administration observed that and decided to expand offensive military capacity - not just reject it, but expand it. It was already way ahead.</p>

<p>That was one reason why Khrushchev placed missiles in Cuba in 1962 to try to redress the balance slightly. That led to what historian Arthur Schlesinger - Kennedy&rsquo;s advisor - called &ldquo;the most dangerous moment in world history” - the Cuban missile crisis. Actually there was another reason for it: the Kennedy administration was carrying out a major terrorist operation against Cuba. Massive terrorism. It&rsquo;s the kind of terrorism that the West doesn&rsquo;t care about because somebody else is the victim.</p>

<p>So it didn&rsquo;t get reported, but it was large-scale. Furthermore, the terror operation - it was called Operation Mongoose - had a plan. It was to culminate in an American invasion in October 1962. The Russians and the Cubans may not have known all the details, but it&rsquo;s likely that they knew this much. That was another reason for placing defensive missiles in Cuba.</p>

<p>Then came very tense weeks as you know. They culminated on October 26th. At that time, B-52s armed with nuclear weapons were ready to attack Moscow. The military instructions permitted crews to launch nuclear war without central control. It was decentralized command. Kennedy himself was leaning towards military action to eliminate the missiles from Cuba.</p>

<p>His own, subjective estimate of the probability of nuclear war was between a third and a half. That would essentially have wiped out the Northern Hemisphere, according to President Eisenhower.</p>

<p>At that point, on October 26th, the letter came from Khrushchev to Kennedy offering to end the crisis. How? By withdrawal of Russian missiles from Cuba in return for withdrawal of U.S. missiles from Turkey. Kennedy in fact didn&rsquo;t even know there were missiles in Turkey. But he was informed of that by his advisors. One of the reasons he didn&rsquo;t know is that they were obsolete and they were being withdrawn anyway.</p>

<p>They were being replaced with far more lethal invulnerable Polaris submarines. So that was the offer: the Russians withdraw missiles from Cuba; the U.S. publicly withdraw obsolete missiles that it&rsquo;s already withdrawing from Turkey, which of course are a much greater threat to Russia than the missiles were in Cuba.</p>

<p>Kennedy refused. That&rsquo;s probably the most horrendous decision in human history, in my opinion. He was taking a huge risk of destroying the world in order to establish a principle: the principle is that we have the right to threaten anyone with destruction anyway we like, but it&rsquo;s a unilateral right. And no one may threaten us, even to try to deter a planned invasion. Much worse than this is the lesson that has been taken away - that Kennedy is praised for his cool courage under pressure. That&rsquo;s the standard version today.</p>

<p>The threats continued. Ten years later, Henry Kissinger called a nuclear alert. 1973. The purpose was to warn the Russians not to intervene in the Israel-Arab conflict. What had happened was that Russia and the United States had agreed to institute a ceasefire. But Kissinger had privately informed Israel that they didn&rsquo;t have to pay any attention to it; they could keep going. Kissinger didn&rsquo;t want the Russians to interfere so he called a nuclear alert.</p>

<p>Going on ten years, Ronald Reagan&rsquo;s in office. His administration decided to probe Russian defenses by simulating air and naval attacks - air attacks into Russia and naval attacks on its border. Naturally this caused considerable alarm in Russia, which unlike the United States is quite vulnerable and had repeatedly been invaded and virtually destroyed. That led to a major war scare in 1983. We have newly released archives that tell us how dangerous it was - much more dangerous than historians had assumed. There&rsquo;s a current CIA study that just came out. It&rsquo;s entitled &ldquo;The War Scare Was for Real&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It was close to nuclear war. It concludes that U.S. intelligence underestimated the threat of a Russian preventative strike, nuclear strike, fearing that the U.S. was attacking them. The most recent issue of The Journal of Strategic Studies - one of the main journals - writes that this almost became a prelude to a preventative nuclear strike. And it continues. I won&rsquo;t go through details, but the Bin Laden assassination is a recent one.</p>

<p>There are now three new threats. I&rsquo;ll try to be brief, but let me mention three cases that are on the front pages right now. North Korea, Iran, China. They&rsquo;re worth looking at. North Korea has been issuing wild, dangerous threats. That&rsquo;s attributed to the lunacy of their leaders. It could be argued that it&rsquo;s the most dangerous, craziest government in the world, and the worst government. It&rsquo;s probably true. But if we want to reduce the threats instead of march blindly in unison, there are a few things to consider.</p>

<p>One of them is that the current crisis began with US-South Korean war games, which included for the first time ever a simulation of a preemptive attack in an all-out war scenario against North Korea. Part of these exercises were simulated nuclear bombings on the borders of North Korea. That brings up some memories for the North Korean leadership.</p>

<p>For example, they can remember that 60 years ago there was a superpower that virtually levelled the entire country and when there was nothing left to bomb, the United States turned to bombing dams. Some of you may recall that you could get the death penalty for that at Nuremberg. It&rsquo;s a war crime. Even if Western intellectuals and the media choose to ignore the documents, the North Korean leadership can read public documents, the official Air Force reports of the time, which are worth reading. I encourage you to read them.</p>

<p>They exulted over the glorious sight of massive floods &ldquo;that scooped clear 27 miles of valley below&rdquo;, devastated 75% of the controlled water supply for North Korea&rsquo;s rice production, sent the commissars scurrying to the press and radio centres to blare to the world the most severe, hate-filled harangues to come from the Communist propaganda mill in the three years of warfare.</p>

<p>To the communists, the smashing of the dams meant primarily the destruction of their chief sustenance: rice. Westerners can little conceive the awesome meaning which the loss of this staple food commodity has for Asians: starvation and slow death. Hence the show of rage, the flare of violent tempers and the threats of reprisals when bombs fell on five irrigation dams. Mostly quotes. Like other potential targets, the crazed North Korean leaders can also read high-level documents which are public, declassified, which outline US strategic doctrine. One of the most important is a study by Clinton&rsquo;s strategic command, STRATCOM. It&rsquo;s about the role of nuclear weapons in the post-Cold War era.</p>

<p>Its central conclusions are: U.S. must retain the right of first strike, even against non-nuclear states; furthermore, nuclear weapons must always be available, at the ready, because they &ldquo;cast a shadow over any crisis or conflict&rdquo;. They frighten adversaries. So they&rsquo;re constantly being used, just as if you&rsquo;re using a gun, going into a store pointing a gun at the store owner. You don&rsquo;t fire it, but you&rsquo;re using the gun. STRATCOM goes on to say planners should not be too rational in determining what the opponent values the most.</p>

<p>All of it has to be targeted. “It hurts to portray ourselves as too fully rational and cool-headed. That the United States may become irrational and vindictive if its vital interests are attacked should be part of the national persona that we project.” It&rsquo;s beneficial for our strategic posture &ldquo;if some elements appear to be potentially out-of-control&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s not Richard Nixon or George W. Bush; it&rsquo;s Bill Clinton.</p>

<p>Again, Western intellectuals and media choose not to look, but potential targets don&rsquo;t have that luxury. There&rsquo;s also a recent history that the North Korean leaders know quite well. I&rsquo;m not going to review it because of lack of time. But it&rsquo;s very revealing.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll just quote mainstream US scholarship. North Korea has been playing tit for tat - reciprocating whenever Washington cooperates, retaliating whenever Washington reneges. Undoubtedly it&rsquo;s a horrible place. But the record does suggest directions that would reduce the threat of war if that were the intention, certainly not military maneuvers and simulated nuclear bombing.</p>

<p>Let me turn to the &ldquo;gravest threat to world peace&rdquo; - those are Obama&rsquo;s words, dutifully repeated in the press: Iran&rsquo;s nuclear program. It raises a couple of questions: Who thinks it&rsquo;s the gravest threat? What is the threat? How can you deal with it, whatever it is?</p>

<p>&lsquo;Who thinks it&rsquo;s a threat?&rsquo; is easy to answer. It&rsquo;s a Western obsession. The U.S. and its allies say it&rsquo;s the gravest threat and not the rest of the world, not the non-aligned countries, not the Arab states. The Arab populations don&rsquo;t like Iran but they don&rsquo;t regard it as much of a threat. They regard the US as the threat. In Iraq and Egypt, for example, the U.S. is regarded as the major threat they face. It&rsquo;s not hard to understand why.</p>

<p>What is the threat? We know the answer from the highest level: the US intelligence and the Pentagon provide estimates to Congress every year. You can read them. The Global Security Analysis - they of course review this. And they say the main threat of a Iranian nuclear program - if they&rsquo;re developing weapons, they don&rsquo;t know. But they say if they&rsquo;re developing weapons, they would be part of their deterrent strategy. The US can&rsquo;t accept that. A state that claims the right to use force and violence anywhere and whenever it wants, cannot accept a deterrent. So they&rsquo;re a threat. That&rsquo;s the threat.</p>

<p>So how do you deal with the threat, whatever it is? Actually, there are ways. I&rsquo;m short of time so I won&rsquo;t go through details but there&rsquo;s one very striking one: We&rsquo;ve just passed an opportunity last December. There was to be an international conference under the auspices of the non-proliferation treaty, UN auspices, in Helsinki to deal with moves to establish a nuclear weapons-free zone in the Middle East. That has overwhelming international support - non-aligned countries; it&rsquo;s been led by the Arab states, Egypt particularly, for decades. Overwhelming support. If it could be carried forward it would certainly mitigate the threat. It might eliminate it. Everyone was waiting to see whether Iran would agree to attend.</p>

<p>In early November, Iran agreed to attend. A couple of days later, Obama cancelled the conference. No conference. The European Parliament passed a resolution calling for it to continue. The Arab states said they were going to proceed anyway, but it can&rsquo;t be done. So we have to live with the gravest threat to world peace. And we possibly have to march on to war which in fact is being predicted.</p>

<p>The population could do something about it if they knew anything about it. But here, the free press enters. In the United States there has literally not been a single word about this anywhere near the mainstream. You can tell me about Europe.</p>

<p>The last potential confrontation is China. It&rsquo;s an interesting one, but time is short so I won&rsquo;t go on.</p>

<p>The last comment I&rsquo;d like to make goes in a somewhat different direction. I mentioned the Magna Carta. That&rsquo;s the foundations of modern law. We will soon be commemorating the 800th anniversary. We won&rsquo;t be celebrating it - more likely interring what little is left of its bones after the flesh has been picked off by Bush and Obama and their colleagues in Europe. And Europe is involved clearly.</p>

<p>But there is another part of Magna Carta which has been forgotten. It had two components. The one is the Charter of Liberties which is being dismantled. The other was called the Charter of the Forests. That called for protection of the commons from the depredations of authority. This is England of course.</p>

<p>The commons were the traditional source of sustenance, of food and fuel and welfare as well. They were nurtured and sustained for centuries by traditional societies collectively. They have been steadily dismantled under the capitalist principle that everything has to be privately owned, which brought with it the perverse doctrine of - what is called the tragedy of the commons - a doctrine which holds that collective possessions will be despoiled so therefore everything has to be privately owned.</p>

<p>The merest glance at the world shows that the opposite is true. It&rsquo;s privatisation that is destroying the commons. That&rsquo;s why the indigenous populations of the world are in the lead in trying to save Magna Carta from final destruction by its inheritors. And they&rsquo;re joined by others. Take say the demonstrators in Gezi Park in trying to block the bulldozers in Taksim Square.</p>

<p>They&rsquo;re trying to save the last part of the commons in Istanbul from the wrecking ball of commercial destruction. This is a kind of a microcosm of the general defense of the commons. It&rsquo;s one part of a global uprising against the violent neo-liberal assault on the population of the world. Europe is suffering severely from it right now. The uprisings have registered some major successes. The most dramatic are Latin America.</p>

<p>In this millennium it has largely freed itself from the lethal grip of Western domination for the first time in 500 years. Other things are happening too. The general picture is pretty grim, I think. But there are shafts of light.</p>

<p>As always through history, there are two trajectories. One leads towards oppression and destruction. The other leads towards freedom and justice. And as always - to adapt Martin Luther King&rsquo;s famous phrase - there are ways to bend the arc of the moral universe towards justice and freedom - and by now even towards survival.</p>

<p>Source: This is a transcript from the DW Global Media Forum in Bonn, Germany republished with permission from chomsky.info</p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The french constitution of 1793.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/10/16/1793-french-constitution/"/>
	    <updated>2013-10-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/10/16/1793-french-constitution/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<hr />

<p>Reading this text, it is extremely surprising to measure the thoughtfulness and care the authors of that time were dedicating to the <strong>common welfare</strong>.
Since then, we have known a long, slow and systematic regression.
We have much to <strong>re-learn</strong> from our forefathers and foremothers.</p>

<hr />

<h1>FRENCH CONSTITUTION of the twenty-fourth of June, 1793.</h1>

<pre><code>    of the republic.
</code></pre>

<ol>
<li><p>The French Republic is one and indivisible.</p>

<pre><code>of the division of the people.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The French people is, for the purpose of exercising its sovereignty, divided into primary assemblies according to cantons.</p></li>

<li><p>For the purpose of administration and justice, it is divided into departments, districts, and municipalities.</p>

<pre><code>of the right of citizenship.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>Every man born and living in France, of twenty-one years of age, and every alien, who has attained the age of twenty-one, and has been domiciled in France one year, and lives from his labor;
or has acquired property;
or has married a French woman;
or has adopted a child;
or supports an aged man;
and finally every alien whom the legislative body has declared as one well deserving of the human race, are admitted to exercise the rights of a French citizen.</p></li>

<li><p>The right of exercising the rights of citizen is lost:
by being naturalized in a foreign state;
by accepting offices of state, or favors which do not proceed from a democratic government;
by being sentenced to dishonorable or corporal punishments, till reinstated in the former state.</p></li>

<li><p>The exercise of the rights of citizen is suspended:
by being in a state of accusation;
by a sentence in contumaciam, so long as this sentence has not been rescinded.
of the sovereignty of the people.</p></li>

<li><p>The sovereign people embraces the whole of French citizens.</p></li>

<li><p>It chooses its deputies directly.</p></li>

<li><p>It delegates to electors the choice of administrators, public civil judges, penal judges, and judges of cassation.</p></li>

<li><p>It deliberates on laws.</p>

<pre><code>of the primary assemblies.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The primary assemblies are formed of the citizens who have resided six months in a canton.</p></li>

<li><p>They consist of no less than 200 and no more than 600 citizens, called together for the purpose of voting.</p></li>

<li><p>They are organized, after a president, secretaries and collectors of votes have been appointed.</p></li>

<li><p>They exercise their own police.</p></li>

<li><p>No one is allowed to appear there with arms.</p></li>

<li><p>The elections are made either by secret or loud voting, at the pleasure of each voter.</p></li>

<li><p>A primary meeting can in no case prescribe more than one manner of voting.</p></li>

<li><p>The collectors of votes note down the votes of those citizens who cannot write, and yet prefer to vote secretly.</p></li>

<li><p>The votes on laws are given by “Yes,” and “No.”</p></li>

<li><p>The elections of primary assemblies are published in the following manner:
The united citizens in the primary assembly at—, numbering—votes, vote for, or vote against, by a majority of—.</p>

<pre><code>of the national representation.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>Population is the only basis of national representation.</p></li>

<li><p>For every 40,000 individuals, one deputy is chosen.</p></li>

<li><p>Every primary assembly which is formed of from 39,000 to 41,000 individuals, chooses directly a deputy.</p></li>

<li><p>The choice is effected by an absolute majority of votes.</p></li>

<li><p>Every assembly makes an abstract of the votes, and sends a commissioner to the appointed central place of general record.</p></li>

<li><p>If at the first voting, no absolute majority be effected, a second meeting shall be held, and those two citizens who had the most votes, shall be voted for again.</p></li>

<li><p>In case of an equal division of votes, the oldest person has the preference, no matter whether he was voted for, or whether he was chosen without it. In case of an equality of age, the casting of lots shall decide.</p></li>

<li><p>Every Frenchman, who enjoys the rights of a citizen, is eligible throughout the whole republic.</p></li>

<li><p>Every deputy belongs to the whole nation.</p></li>

<li><p>In case of non-acceptance, of abdication, or expiration of office, or of the death of a deputy, the primary assembly which had chosen him shall choose a substitute.</p></li>

<li><p>A deputy who hands in his resignation, cannot leave his post till his successor shall have been appointed.</p></li>

<li><p>The French people assembles every year on the 1st of May for election.</p></li>

<li><p>It proceeds thereto, whatever the number of citizens [present] may be, who have a right to vote.</p></li>

<li><p>Extraordinary primary meetings are held at the demand of one-fifth of the eligible citizens.</p></li>

<li><p>The meeting is, in this case, called by the municipal authority of the usual place of assembly.</p></li>

<li><p>These extraordinary meetings can transact business only when at least more than one-half of the qualified voters are present.</p>

<pre><code>of the electoral assemblies.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The citizens, united in primary assemblies, nominate in proportion of 200 citizens, (they may be present or not,) one elector; two, for from 301 to 400;three, for from 501 to 600.</p></li>

<li><p>The holding of election meetings, and the manner of election, are the same as in the primary meetings.</p>

<pre><code>of the legislative body.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The legislative body is one, indivisible and continual.</p></li>

<li><p>Its session lasts one year.</p></li>

<li><p>It assembles on the 1st of July.</p></li>

<li><p>The national assembly cannot be organized, unless at least one more than one-half of the deputies are present.</p></li>

<li><p>The deputies can, at no time, be held answerable, accused or condemned on account of opinions uttered within the legislative body.</p></li>

<li><p>In criminal cases, they may be arrested if caught in the act;but the warrant of arrest and the warrant of committal can be issued only by the legislative body.</p>

<pre><code>mode of procedure of the legislative body.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The sessions of the national assembly are public.</p></li>

<li><p>The debates in their sessions shall be printed.</p></li>

<li><p>It cannot deliberate, unless it consist of 200 members.</p></li>

<li><p>It cannot refuse to members the floor, in the order in which they demand the same.</p></li>

<li><p>It decides by a majority of those present.</p></li>

<li><p>Fifty members have the right to demand a call by names.</p></li>

<li><p>It has the right of censorship on the conduct of the members in its midst.</p></li>

<li><p>It exercises the power of police at the place of its sessions, and within the whole extent of its environs.</p>

<pre><code>of the functions of the legislative body.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The legislative body proposes laws, and issues decrees.</p></li>

<li><p>By the general name of law, are understood the provisions of the legislative body which concern:
the civil and penal legislation;
the general administration of revenues and of the ordinary expenditures of the republic;
the national domains;
the inscription, alloy, stamp and names of coins; declaration of war;
every new general division of the French territory; public instruction;
public demonstrations of honor to the memory of great men.</p></li>

<li><p>By the particular name of decrees are understood those enactments of the legislative body, which concern:
the annual establishment of the land and marine forces; the permission or refusal of the marching of foreign troops
through the French territory; the admission of foreign vessels of war into the ports of the republic;
the measures for the common peace and safety; the distribution of annual and momentary relief and of public works;
the orders for the stamping of coins of every description; the unforeseen and extraordinary expenses;
the local and particular orders for an administration, a commune, and any kind of public works;
the defence of the territory;
the ratification of treaties;
the nomination and removal of the commander-in-chief of the army;
the carrying into effect the responsibility of members of the executive council, and of public officers;
the accusation of discovered conspiracies against the common safety of the republic;
every alteration in the division of the French territory; the national rewards.</p>

<pre><code>of the making of laws.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>A notice must precede the introduction of a bill.</p></li>

<li><p>Not till after a fortnight from the giving of notice can the debate begin, and the law be temporarily accepted.</p></li>

<li><p>The proposed law is printed and sent to all the communes of the republic, under the address of, Proposed law.</p></li>

<li><p>If, forty days after the sending in of the proposed law, of the absolute majority of departments, one-tenth of all the primary meetings, legally assembled by the departments, have not protested, the bill is accepted and becomes a law.</p></li>

<li><p>If protest be made, the legislative body calls together the primary meetings.</p>

<pre><code>of the superscription of laws and decrees.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The laws, decrees, sentences, and all public transactions are superscribed:
In the name of the French people, in the—year of the French Republic.</p>

<pre><code>of the executive power.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>There shall be an executive council, consisting of twenty-four members.</p></li>

<li><p>The electoral assembly of each department nominates a candidate. The legislative body chooses from this general list the members of the executive council.</p></li>

<li><p>It shall be renewed each half session of every legislature, in the last months of its session.</p></li>

<li><p>The executive council has the management and supervision of the general administration. Its activity is limited to the execution of laws and decrees of the legislative body.</p></li>

<li><p>It appoints, but not out of its midst, the highest agents of the general administration of the republic.</p></li>

<li><p>The legislative body establishes the number of these agents, and their business.</p></li>

<li><p>These agents form no council. They are separated one from the other, and have no relation among themselves. They exercise no personal power.</p></li>

<li><p>The executive council chooses, but not from its midst, the foreign agents of the republic.</p></li>

<li><p>It negotiates treaties.</p></li>

<li><p>The members of the executive council are, in case of violation of duties, accused by the legislative body.</p></li>

<li><p>The executive council is responsible for the non-execution of the laws and decrees, and the abuses, of which it does not give notice.</p></li>

<li><p>It recalls and substitutes the agents at pleasure.</p></li>

<li><p>It is obliged, if possible, to inform the judicial authorities regarding them.</p>

<pre><code>of the mutual relations between the executive council, and the legislative body.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The executive council shall have its seat near the legislative body. It shall have admittance to, and a special seat at the place of session.</p></li>

<li><p>It shall every time be heard, when it shall have to give account.</p></li>

<li><p>The legislative body shall call it into its midst, in whole or in part, when it is thought necessary.</p>

<pre><code>of the administrative authorities and the municipalities.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>There shall be a municipal authority in each commune of the republic; and in each district an intermediate administration; and in each department a central administration.</p></li>

<li><p>The municipal officers are chosen by the assemblies of the commune.</p></li>

<li><p>The administrators are chosen by the electoral assemblies of the departments and of the district.</p></li>

<li><p>The municipalities and the administrative authorities are annually renewed one-half.</p></li>

<li><p>The administrative authorities and municipal officers have not a representative character. They can, in no case, limit the resolves of the legislative body, nor the execution of them.</p></li>

<li><p>The legislative body assigns the business of the municipal officers and of the administrative authorities, the rules regarding their subordination, and the punishments to which they may become liable.</p></li>

<li><p>The sessions of the municipalities and of the administrative authorities are held in public.</p>

<pre><code>of civil justice.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The civil and penal code is the same for the whole republic.</p></li>

<li><p>No encroachment can be made upon the right of citizens to have their matters in dispute decided on by arbitrators of their own choice.</p></li>

<li><p>The decision of these arbitrators is final, unless the citizens have reserved the right of protesting.</p></li>

<li><p>There shall be justices of the peace, chosen by the citizens of the districts, appointed by law.</p></li>

<li><p>They shall conciliate and hold court without fees.</p></li>

<li><p>Their number and extent of power shall be established by the legislative body.</p></li>

<li><p>There shall be public judges of arbitration, who are chosen by electoral assemblies.</p></li>

<li><p>Their number and districts are fixed by the legislative body.</p></li>

<li><p>They shall decide on matters in controversy, which have not been brought to a final decision by private arbitrators or by the justices of the peace.</p></li>

<li><p>They shall deliberate publicly. They shall vote with loud voice.
They shall decide in the last resort on oral pleadings, or on a simple petition, without legal forms and without cost. They shall assign the reasons of their decisions.</p></li>

<li><p>The justices of the peace and the public arbitrators are chosen annually.</p>

<pre><code>of criminal justice.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>In criminal cases, no citizen can be put on trial, except a true bill of complaint be found by a jury, or by the legislative body.
The accused shall have advocates, either chosen by themselves, or appointed officially. The proceedings are in public. The state of facts and the intention are passed upon by a jury. The punishment is executed by a criminal authority.</p></li>

<li><p>The criminal judges are chosen annually by the electoral assemblies.</p>

<pre><code>of the court of cassation.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>There is a court of cassation for the whole republic.</p></li>

<li><p>This court takes no cognizance of the state of facts.
It decides on the violation of matters of form, and on transgressions expressed by law.</p></li>

<li><p>The members of this court are appointed annually through the electoral assemblies.</p>

<pre><code>of the general taxes.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>No citizen is excluded from the honorable obligation to contribute towards the public expenses.</p>

<pre><code>of the national treasury.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The national treasury is the central point of the revenues and expenses of the republic.</p></li>

<li><p>It is managed by public accountants, whom the legislative body shall elect.</p></li>

<li><p>These agents are supervised by officers of account, whom the legislative body shall elect, but who cannot be taken from their own body: they are responsible for abuses of which they do not give legal notice to the courts.</p>

<pre><code>of the rendition of accounts.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The accounts of the agents of the national treasury, and those of the administrators of public moneys are taken annually, by responsible commissioners appointed by the executive council.</p></li>

<li><p>Those persons appointed to revise the accounts are under the supervision of commissioners, who are elected by the legislative body, not out of their own number; and they are responsible for the frauds and mistakes of accounts, of which they do not give notice.</p>

<pre><code>__The legislative body preserves the accounts__


of the military forces of the republic.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The general military power of the republic consists of the whole people.</p></li>

<li><p>The republic supports, also, in times of peace, a paid land and marine force.</p></li>

<li><p>All Frenchmen are soldiers; all shall be exercised in the use of arms.</p></li>

<li><p>There is no generalissimo.</p></li>

<li><p>The distinction of grade, the military marks of distinction and subordination, exist only in service and in time of its duration.</p></li>

<li><p>The general military force is used for the preservation of order and peace in the interior; it acts only on a written requisition of the constituted authorities.</p></li>

<li><p>The general military force against foreign enemies is under the command of the executive council.</p></li>

<li><p>No armed body can deliberate.</p>

<pre><code>of the national convention.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>If of the absolute majority of departments, the tenth part of their regularly formed primary assemblies demand a revision of the constitution, or an alteration of some of its articles; the legislative body is obliged to call together all primary assemblies of the republic, in order to ascertain whether a national convention shall be called.</p></li>

<li><p>The national convention is formed in like manner as the legislatures, and unites in itself the highest power.</p></li>

<li><p>It is occupied, as regards the constitution, only with those subjects which caused its being called together.</p>

<pre><code>of the relations of the french republic towards foreign nations.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The French nation is the friend and natural ally of free nations.</p></li>

<li><p>It does not interfere with the affairs of government of other nations. It suffers no interference of other nations with its own.</p></li>

<li><p>It serves as a place of refuge for all who, on account of liberty, are banished from their native country.
These it refuses to deliver up to tyrants.</p></li>

<li><p>It concludes no peace with an enemy that holds possession of its territory.</p>

<pre><code>of the guaranty of rights.
</code></pre></li>

<li><p>The constitution guarantees to all Frenchmen equality, liberty, security, property, the public debt, free exercise of religion, general instruction, public assistance, absolute liberty of the press, the right of petition, the right to hold popular assemblies, and the enjoyment of all the rights of man.</p></li>

<li><p>The French republic respects loyalty, courage, age, filial love, misfortune. It places the constitution under the guaranty of all virtues.</p></li>

<li><p>The declaration of the rights of man and the constitution shall be engraven on tables, to be placed in the midst of the legislative body, and in public places.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>(Signed) COLLOT D&rsquo;HERBOIS, President.</p>

<p>Durand-Maillane, Ducos, Meaulle,
Charles de la  Croix Gossuin, P. A. Laloy,
Secretary</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/thinking.jpg" alt="Capitalism" title="to learn from our ancestors" />
</p>

<hr />
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Old Story, but Useful Lessons? Climate Change as of September 2013.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/10/05/hansen-climate-sensitivity/"/>
	    <updated>2013-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/10/05/hansen-climate-sensitivity/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~jeh1/mailings/2013/20130926_PTRSpaperDiscussion.pdf" target="_blank">original document</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/panel-3.jpg" alt="Climate" title="Climate change, an old story." />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by James Hansen - September, 26th 2013</h2>

<p>An Old Story, but Useful Lessons</p>

<p>26 September 2013
James Hansen
&ldquo;Climate Sensitivity, Sea Level and Atmospheric Carbon Dioxide&rdquo; was published last week, in the venerable Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society, and is freely available.</p>

<p>I already commented on the paper (<a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~jeh1/mailings/2013/20130415_Exaggerations.pdf" target="_blank">Exaggeration, Jumping the Gun, and Venus Syndrome</a>), as has <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/climate/2013/09/17/1892241/hansen-climate-sensitivity-uninhabitable/" target="_blank">Joe Romm</a>, so, for the sake of getting onto other matters, I make only a few comments here.</p>

<p>Paleoclimate, changes of climate over Earth&rsquo;s history, provide valuable insights about the effects of human perturbations to climate, even though there is no close paleoclimate analog of the strong, rapid forcing that humans are applying to the climate system. International discussions of human-made climate change (e.g., IPCC) rely heavily on global climate models, with less emphasis on inferences from the paleo record. A proper thing to say is that paleoclimate data and global modeling need to go hand in hand to develop best understanding &ndash; almost everyone will agree with that. However, it seems to me that paleo is still getting short-shrifted and underutilized. In contrast, there is a tendency in the literature to treat an ensemble of model runs as if its distribution function is a distribution function for the truth, i.e., for the real world. Wow. What a terrible misunderstanding. Today&rsquo;s models have many assumptions and likely many flaws in common, so varying the parameters in them does not give a probability distribution for the real world, yet that is often implicitly assumed to be the case. But enough introduction.</p>

<p><strong>1. &ldquo;Fast-Feedback&rdquo; Climate Sensitivity</strong></p>

<p>Jule Charney, in discussions around the time of the 1979 NAS CO2 study, focused on the notion of what we can call the &ldquo;fast-feedback equilibrium climate sensitivity&rdquo;. In the real world, the transient climate response to a forcing does not allow a clean separation of processes into fast and slow, because the transient climate response is inherently slow, due to the great inertia of the system, especially the ocean &ndash; and that allows slow feedbacks to begin to operate while the fast ones are still growing. Nevertheless, the concept is very useful, and the paleoclimate record allows us to separate the effects of fast and slow feedbacks.</p>

<p>Charney included water vapor, cloud and sea ice changes in response to a changing climate in the category of fast feedbacks. He would also have included aerosol changes in response to climate change as a fast feedback, but climate models then did not yet simulate aerosol changes, so the aerosol feedback was not addressed.</p>

<p>Climate simulations took ice sheets, greenhouse gases (other than water vapor), and the vegetation distribution as fixed boundary conditions. These were considered to be slow feedbacks, unlikely to change much on time scales of interest (decades, up to a century or so).</p>

<p>Aerosols warrant a comment. Human-made aerosols are a climate forcing, as is their indirect effects on clouds. However, the aerosol changes that occur in response to climate change are logically treated as a fast feedback.</p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/climateChange-anOldStory/20130926_PTRSpaperDiscussion.bmp" alt="ClimateChange" title="Climate change, an old story." />
</p>

<hr />

<pre><code>Fig. 4. Surface temperature estimate for the past 65.5 million years,
including an expanded time scale for (b)
the Pliocene and Pleistocene (past 5+ million years) and (c) the last 800,000 years.
The red curve has 500 kilo year resolution.
Data for this and other figures are available in the electronic Supplementary Material.
</code></pre>

<p>Comparison of different climate states, e.g., neighboring glacial and interglacial periods, both of which can be assumed to be in near equilibrium with their respective boundary conditions, potentially can yield an accurate assessment of the fast-feedback climate sensitivity, because there is reasonably good knowledge of the boundary conditions in both climate states, i.e., ice sheet size, vegetation distribution, and long-lived greenhouse gas amounts (CO2, CH4, N2O).</p>

<p>We show that a single fast-feedback sensitivity, for the most part, fits the entire 800,000 year ice core record quite well. That sensitivity is approximately 3°C for doubled CO2. Remarkably the biggest source of uncertainty is not the change in boundary conditions between glacial and interglacial states, but rather the change of global temperature. Was global temperature during the last ice age 4.5°C colder than the Holocene? 3°C colder? 6°C colder? There is still a wide disagreement about that, leading us to conclude that the equilibrium sensitivity is 3±1°C.</p>

<p>We suggest that perhaps the most useful way to improve evaluation of fast-feedback climate sensitivity would be a focused program to evaluate global temperature during the last ice age. It is strange and unfortunate that the uncertainty is about the same now as it was 30 years ago.</p>

<p>However, we also note that there are issues about using the Holocene (current interglacial period, about 10,000 years long) as a measuring point, because of changes within the Holocene and the possibility that humans contributed to them. Climate change from the prior glacial to interglacial period, the Eemian (~125,000 years ago), would provide a clean alternative to focus on. Despite uncertainties in the paleo data, this empirical climate sensitivity is much better than that provided by attempts to extract a value from observed climate change in the past century. We don&rsquo;t know the net climate forcing, because human-made aerosol changes and their effect on clouds are not known. The paleo case does not suffer that problem, because paleo aerosol and cloud changes are fast climate feedbacks, except perhaps some human effect in the Holocene.</p>

<p><strong>2. Slow Feedbacks, Ice Sheet Response Time</strong></p>

<p>Additional insight is provided by the longer paleoclimate record, not only glacial-to-interglacial changes, but climate change over the entire Cenozoic era, all the way back to an ice-free planet. For example, we can see effects of both amplifying and diminishing slow feedbacks.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Hyperthermal events&rdquo; such as the Paleocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum (PETM), a global warming of at least 5°C in response to sudden injection of a huge amount of carbon into the climate system, probably from thawing methane hydrates and/or Antarctic permafrost and peat, are eventually followed by a strong diminishing feedback as the excess carbon is drawn down and deposited as carbonates on the ocean floor. However, the time scale of this diminishing feedback is of the order of 100,000 years. This same slow feedback will also draw down the human-made carbon injection into the atmosphere, on the time scale of 100,000 years.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, slow feedbacks are amplifying on time scales that humans care about: decades, centuries, even millennia. As the planet warms, for example, ice sheets melt, exposing a darker surface that increases warming. Also warming causes a net release of long-lived greenhouse gases from the ocean and soil. Vegetation changes that occur as climate warms from today&rsquo;s situation will also have a significant amplifying effect, as forests move into tundra regions in North America and Eurasia. This feedback contributed to Pliocene warmth.</p>

<p>How fast will the amplifying feedbacks come into play? The paleoclimate record does not include a large positive (warming) forcing introduced at the speed of the human-made change. However, the paleo climate changes reveal little evidence of a significant lag between warming and slow feedbacks. That includes sea level change in response to warming; global temperature and sea level changes are nearly synchronous in the paleoclimate record. Our paper shows that ice sheet models are too lethargic &ndash; they do not reproduce the rapid sea level change in the data.</p>

<p>Of course the ocean&rsquo;s thermal inertia causes a lag between the rapid human-made change of CO2 and global temperature. Also, even though we cannot detect a lag between slowly changing paleo temperatures and sea level, in the case of human-made warming the lag associated with the ice sheet response is surely significant compared with the rapidity of the growing human forcing. However, we have neither a good paleo analog for the human forcing nor as yet adequate ice sheet models to let us determine the time scale of the response.</p>

<p>In my opinion, multi-meter sea level rise will occur this century, if the huge business-as-usual climate forcing actually occurs. I have described in prior papers reasons to expect non-linear rapid ice sheet response, if ocean warming melts the ice shelves now buttressing the ice sheets. I expect the new IPCC report will only begin to inch toward that answer. On the other hand, I think there is a good chance that we will come to our senses in the next several years and begin to rapidly phase down emissions &ndash; in which case we might still avoid really large sea level rise.</p>

<p><strong>3. The Venus Syndrome (repeated from 15 April post, as there was a misstatement in my book, Storms of My Grandchildren)</strong></p>

<p>I get questions from the public about the Venus Syndrome: is there a danger of &ldquo;runaway&rdquo; greenhouse warming on Earth leading to Venus-like conditions? Related questions concern specific positive (amplifying) feedbacks such as methane hydrates: as warming thaws tundra and destabilizes methane hydrates on continental shelves, thus releasing methane, won&rsquo;t this cause more warming, thus more methane release, thus more warming &ndash; a runaway warming?</p>

<p>Amplifying feedbacks. Let&rsquo;s consider a positive climate forcing (say a solar irradiance increase or CO2 increase) that causes a unit of warming. Let&rsquo;s ask how this unit warming will be amplified by a very strong feedback, one that increases the initial warming by 50%. The added warming of 0.5 induces more feedback, by 0.5×0.5 = 0.25, and so on, the final response being 1 + 0.5 + 0.25 + 0.125 + &hellip; = 2. So this very strong feedback causes the final warming to be twice as large as it would have been without the feedback. But it is not a runaway effect.</p>

<p>The strongest feedback that we observe on Earth today, from water vapor, is almost as strong as this example. Other feedbacks are occurring at the same time, some amplifying and some diminishing (negative). The net effect of all fast feedbacks can be assessed by comparing different well-characterized climate states in Earth&rsquo;s history, as described in our paper,4 treating slow changes such as ice sheet size as specified boundary conditions. It turns out that the net effect of fast feedbacks is to amplify the global temperature response by about a factor of 2-3.1</p>

<p>Other feedbacks become important on longer time scales. As the planet becomes warmer the ice sheet area tends to decrease, exposing a darker surface that absorbs more sunlight. And as the planet warms the ocean and land release long-lived greenhouse gases, mainly CO2 and CH4 (methane). Thus Earth&rsquo;s climate is dominated by amplifying feedbacks on time scales of 10-100,000 years and less. For this reason, Earth can be whipsawed between glacial and interglacial conditions by the small climate forcings caused by perturbations of Earth&rsquo;s orbit.[i]</p>

<p>The dominance of amplifying feedbacks and the resulting high climate sensitivity make Earth susceptible to what we can call a mini-runaway. By mini-runaway, I refer to a case with an amplifying feedback large enough that the total feedback reaches runaway (the infinite series above does not converge), but eventually that process runs out of fuel. Evidence of such behavior is provided by hyperthermal events2 in Earth&rsquo;s history, sudden rapid warmings that occurred during periods of more gradual warming.</p>

<p>The most studied hyperthermal is the PETM (Paleocene Eocene Thermal Maximum), which occurred in the middle of a 10 million year period of gradual warming. A rapid warming spike occurred in conjunction with injection of a large amount of CO2 into the climate system on a time scale of the order of a millennium. The source of the rapid CO2 increase is most commonly suggested to have been the melting of methane hydrates due to a warming ocean, with an alternative suggestion being incineration of large peat deposits, especially on Antarctica.</p>

<p>Whatever the CO2 source, global temperature increased about 6°C over several millennia. The continental weathering process provided a negative feedback, as a pumped-up hydrologic cycle drew down atmospheric CO2 and deposited it as carbonate on the ocean floor. However, this feedback requires tens of thousands of years, so the rapid warming stopped only when the fuel source was depleted.</p>

<p>Are hyperthermals relevant now, as a possible amplification of fossil fuel warming? Unfortunately, they may be. Burning all fossil fuels would produce such large ocean warming, which would continue to exist for centuries, that ignition of a hyperthermal amplification of global warming is a possibility. Consequences are unclear. Carbon release in prior hyperthermals occurred over a millennium or more, at a rate up to ~ 5 GtC/year. This can be compared with the present global rate of fossil fuel burning, which is ~ 9 GtC/year.</p>

<p>It is instructive to consider the task of dealing with such continuing carbon release, in the event that we did set it off. Humanity could defuse a continuous release of 5 GtC/year, thus avoiding hyperthermal warming, by capturing and sequestering the carbon. The American Physical Society estimates [ii] the cost of capture and sequestration as ~ $2 trillion per GtC. Given that the United States is responsible for 26% of the fossil fuel CO2 in the air today [iii], the U.S. cost share for removing 5 GtC/year would be ~$2.6 trillion each year. Technology development might be able to lower that cost, but fundamental energy constraints imply that cost reduction at most will be a factor of a few. [iv]</p>

<p>We had better be sure to avoid a mini-runaway. If we phase out fossil fuels rapidly and move to a clean energy future in accord with a scenario that my colleagues and I have described8, we could be reasonably confident of avoiding that situation. We know that prior interglacial periods were moderately warmer than the current (Holocene) interglacial. A fossil fuel emissions scenario similar to the one we have defined is needed for other reasons, especially for the purpose of maintaining reasonably stable shorelines, i.e., avoiding sea level rise of many meters, which would destroy thousands of coastal cities all around the world.</p>

<p>In contrast, if we burn all the fossil fuels it is certain that sea level would eventually rise by tens of meters. The only argument is how soon the rise of several meters needed to destroy habitability of all coastal cities would occur. It is also possible that burning all fossil fuels would eventually set off a hyperthermal event, a mini-runaway. Is it conceivable that we could get a runaway leading all the way to the Venus Syndrome, Venus-like conditions on Earth?</p>

<p>Runaway Greenhouse. Venus today has a surface pressure of about 90 bars, compared with 1 bar on Earth. The Venus atmosphere is mostly CO2. The huge atmospheric depth and CO2 amount are the reason Venus has a surface temperature of nearly 500øC.</p>

<p>Venus and Earth probably had similar early atmospheric compositions, but on Earth the carbon is mostly in Earth&rsquo;s crust, not in the atmosphere. As long as Earth has an ocean most of the carbon will continue to be in the crust, because, although volcanoes inject crustal carbon into the atmosphere as CO2, the weathering process removes CO2 from the air and deposits it on the ocean floor as carbonates. Venus once had an ocean, but being closer to the Sun, its atmosphere became hot enough that hydrogen could escape from the upper atmosphere, as confirmed today by the extreme depletion on Venus of normal hydrogen relative to heavy hydrogen (deuterium), the lighter hydrogen being able to escape the gravitational field of Venus more readily.</p>

<p>Earth can &ldquo;achieve&rdquo; Venus-like conditions, in the sense of ~90 bar surface pressure, only after first getting rid of its ocean via escape of hydrogen to space. This is conceivable if the atmosphere warms enough that the troposphere expands into the present stratosphere, thus eliminating the tropopause (see Fig. 7 in our paper4 in press), causing water vapor to be transported more rapidly to the upper atmosphere, where it can be dissociated and the hydrogen can then escape to space. Thus extreme warming of the lower atmosphere with elimination of the cold-trap tropopause seems to be the essential physical process required for transition from Earth-like to Venus-like conditions.</p>

<p>If Earth&rsquo;s lower atmosphere did warm enough to accelerate escape of hydrogen it would still take at least hundreds of millions of years for the ocean to be lost to space. Additional time would be needed for massive amounts of CO2 to accumulate in the atmosphere from volcanoes associated with plate tectonics and convection in Earth&rsquo;s mantle. So Venus-like conditions in the sense of 90 bar surface pressure and surface temperature of several hundred degrees are only plausible on billion-year time scales.</p>

<p>Is it possible, with the present surface pressure of ~ 1 bar, for Earth&rsquo;s surface to become so hot that that the planet is practically uninhabitable by humans? That is the situation I depicted in &ldquo;Storms of My Grandchildren&rdquo; [v], which was presumed to be a consequence of burning all fossil fuels over a period of several centuries, with warming further amplified by ignition of PETM-like hyperthermal warming. Support for the possibility of large warming was provided by global climate model simulations indicating an upturn in climate sensitivity at climate forcings ~10 W/m2 (Fig. 30 in &ldquo;Storms&rdquo;10). If other forcings are unchanged, a 10 W/m2 forcing requires a CO2 increase by a factor of 4-8 times its pre-industrial amount (~280 ppm) &ndash; an increase that is possible if all extractable fossil fuels are burned4,8. Other complex global climate models also find an upturn in climate sensitivity or climate model &ldquo;crash&rdquo; when CO2 amount reaches such high levels [vi], raising the question of whether such a level of climate forcing is already trending toward a runaway greenhouse effect.</p>

<p>The concept of a runaway greenhouse effect was introduced [vii] by considering a highly idealized situation with specified troposphere-stratosphere atmospheric structure, a simple approximation for atmospheric radiation, and no inclusion of how clouds might change as climate changes, as is appropriate for introduction of a concept. More recent studies [viii] relax some of the idealizations and are sufficient to show that Earth is not now near a runaway situation, but the idealizations are still sufficient that the studies do not provide a picture of where Earth is headed if all fossil fuels are burned.</p>

<p>An alternative promising approach is to employ the fundamental equations for atmospheric structure and motions, i.e., the conservation equations for energy, momentum, mass, and water, and the ideal gas law. These equations form the core of atmospheric general circulation models and global climate models. However, today&rsquo;s global models generally contain representations of so many additional physical processes that the models are difficult to use for investigations of extreme climatic situations, because invariably some approximations in the scores of equations become invalid in extreme climates. In contrast, my long-term colleague Gary Russell has developed a global model that solves the fundamental equations with the minimum additional physics needed to investigate climate sensitivity over the full range from snowball Earth to a hothouse uninhabitable planet. The additional physics includes accurate spectral dependence of solar and thermal radiation, convection, and clouds. Although the precision of the results depends on the representation of clouds, we suggest that the simple prescription employed is likely to correctly capture essence of cloud change in response to climate change.</p>

<p>We use the Russell model in our paper to show that the tropopause rises in response to the global warming that occurs with larger and larger CO2 amounts (Fig. 7 in our paper 4), and cloud cover decreases with increasing CO2. In consequence climate sensitivity initially increases as CO2 increases, consistent with the upturn of sensitivity found in more complex global climate models11. With the more realistic physics in the Russell model the runaway water vapor feedback that exists with idealized concepts12 does not occur. However, the high climate sensitivity has implications for the habitability of the planet, should all fossil fuels actually be burned. Furthermore, we show that the calculated climate sensitivity is consistent with global temperature and CO2 amounts that are estimated to have existed at earlier times in Earth&rsquo;s history when the planet was ice-free.</p>

<p>One implication is that if we should &ldquo;succeed&rdquo; in digging up and burning all fossil fuels, some parts of the planet would become literally uninhabitable, with some time in the year having wet bulb temperature exceeding 35øC. At such temperatures, for reasons of physiology and physics, humans cannot survive, because even under ideal conditions of rest and ventilation, it is physically impossible for the environment to carry away the 100 W of metabolic heat that a human body generates when it is at rest [ix]. Thus even a person lying quietly naked in hurricane force winds would be unable to survive. Temperatures even several degrees below this extreme limit would be sufficient to make a region practically uninhabitable for living and working.</p>

<p>The picture that emerges for Earth sometime in the distant future, if we should dig up and burn every fossil fuel, is thus consistent with that depicted in &ldquo;Storms&rdquo; &ndash; an ice-free Antarctica and a desolate planet without human inhabitants. Although temperatures in the Himalayas may have become seductive, it is doubtful that the many would allow the wealthy few to appropriate this territory to themselves or that humans would survive with the extermination of most other species on the planet. At least one sentence in &ldquo;Storms&rdquo; will need to be corrected in the next edition: even with burning of all fossil fuels the tropical ocean does not &ldquo;boil&rdquo;. But it is not an exaggeration to suggest, based on best available scientific evidence, that burning all fossil fuels could result in the planet being not only ice-free but human-free.</p>

<hr />

<p>1 Global warming in response to doubled CO2 or a 2% increase of solar irradiance would be 1.2°C in the absence of climate feedbacks. Thus the net fast feedback factor of 2-3 yields 2.4-3.6°C warming for doubled CO2.</p>

<p>2 A brief discussion of hyperthermals on page 3 of our paper4 includes many references to the scientific literature.</p>

<hr />

<p>i Hansen, J, M Sato, P Kharecha, G Russell, DW Lea, M Siddall, 2007: <a href="http://rsta.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/365/1856/1925" target="_blank">Climate change and trace gases.</a> Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A, 365, 1925-1954, doi:10.1098/rsta.2007.2052.</p>

<p>ii APS (2011) Direct Air Capture of CO2 with Chemicals: A Technology Assessment for the APS Panel on Public Affairs. American Physical Society. <a href="http://www.aps.org/policy/reports/assessments/upload/dac2011.pdf">http://www.aps.org/policy/reports/assessments/upload/dac2011.pdf</a>.</p>

<p>iii Hansen, J et al., 2013: Scientific prescription to avoid dangerous climate change to protect young people, future generations, and nature (submitted for publication).</p>

<p>iv House KZ, Baclig AC, Ranjan M, van Nierop EA, Wilcox J, Herzog HJ, 2011: Economic and energetic analysis of capturing CO2 from ambient air. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 108, 20428-20433. v Hansen J, 2009: Storms of My Grandchildren, 304 pp., Bloomsbury USA, New York.</p>

<p>vi Lunt DJ et al., 2012: A model-data comparison for a multi-model ensemble of early Eocene atmosphere-ocean simulations: EoMIP. Clim. Past 8, 1717-1736.</p>

<p>vii Ingersoll AP, 1969: Runaway greenhouse - a history of water on Venus. J. Atmos. Sci. 26, 1191-1198.</p>

<p>viii Goldblatt C, Watson AJ, 2012: The runaway greenhouse: implications for future climate change, geoengineering and planetary atmospheres. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A 370, 4197-4216.</p>

<p>ix Sherwood, SC, and Huber, M. An adaptability limit to climate change due to heat stress. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 2010, 107:9552-9555.</p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Iraq deaths]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/09/16/justice-foreign-policy/"/>
	    <updated>2013-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/09/16/justice-foreign-policy/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.justforeignpolicy.org/iraq/" target="_blank">original source</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/theFall.jpg" alt="statut politique" title="morts en Irak" />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>Reproduced here by Patrick Toca - Septembre 16, 2013</h2>

<p>The number is shocking and sobering.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.justforeignpolicy.org/iraq" _fcksavedurl="http://www.justforeignpolicy.org/iraq"  target="_blank"><img src="http://www.justforeignpolicy.org/images/iraqdeaths.gif" _fcksavedurl="http://www.justforeignpolicy.org/images/iraqdeaths.gif" alt="Iraq Deaths Estimator" border="0" /></a></p>

<p>It is at least 10 times greater than most estimates cited in the US media, yet it is based on a scientific study of violent Iraqi deaths caused by the U.S.-led invasion of March 2003.</p>

<p>A study, published in prestigious medical journal The Lancet, estimated that over 600,000 Iraqis had been killed as a result of the invasion as of July 2006. Iraqis have continued to be killed since then. The death counter provides a rough daily update of this number based on a rate of increase derived from the Iraq Body Count.</p>

<p>The estimate that over a million Iraqis have died received independent confirmation from a prestigious British polling agency in January 2008. Opinion Research Business estimated that the death toll between March 2003 and August 2007 was 1,033,000.</p>

<p>This devastating human toll demands greater recognition. It eclipses the Rwandan genocide and our leaders are directly responsible. Little wonder they do not publicly cite it.</p>

<p>The death counter provides a rough daily update of this number based on a rate of increase derived from the <a href="http://www.iraqbodycount.org/about/" target="_blank"><strong>«Iraq Body Count»</strong></a>.</p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Go data structures: Interfaces.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/09/14/go-data-structures-interfaces/"/>
	    <updated>2013-09-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/09/14/go-data-structures-interfaces/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://research.swtch.com/interfaces/" target="_blank">original document</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/go-data-structures-interfaces/Interfaces.jpg" alt="Interfaces" title="Interfaces" />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by Russ Cox - December 1, 2009</h2>

<p>Go&rsquo;s interfaces—static, checked at compile time, dynamic when asked for—are, for me, the most exciting part of Go from a language design point of view. If I could export one feature of Go into other languages, it would be interfaces.</p>

<p>This post is my take on the implementation of interface values in the “gc” compilers: 6g, 8g, and 5g. Over at Airs, Ian Lance Taylor has written <a href="http://www.airs.com/blog/archives/277" target="_blank">two posts</a> about the implementation of interface values in gccgo. The implementations are more alike than different: the biggest difference is that this post has pictures.</p>

<p>Before looking at the implementation, let&rsquo;s get a sense of what it must support.</p>

<p><strong>Usage</strong></p>

<p>Go&rsquo;s interfaces let you use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duck_typing" target="_blank">duck typing</a> like you would in a purely dynamic language like Python but still have the compiler catch obvious mistakes like passing an int where an object with a Read method was expected, or like calling the Read method with the wrong number of arguments. To use interfaces, first define the interface type (say, ReadCloser):</p>

<pre><code>type ReadCloser interface {
    Read(b []byte) (n int, err os.Error)
    Close()
}
</code></pre>

<p>and then define your new function as taking a ReadCloser. For example, this function calls Read repeatedly to get all the data that was requested and then calls Close:</p>

<pre><code>func ReadAndClose(r ReadCloser, buf []byte) (n int, err os.Error) {
    for len(buf) &gt; 0 &amp;&amp; err == nil {
        var nr int
        nr, err = r.Read(buf)
        n += nr
        buf = buf[nr:]
    }
    r.Close()
    return
}
</code></pre>

<p>The code that calls ReadAndClose can pass a value of any type as long as it has Read and Close methods with the right signatures. And, unlike in languages like Python, if you pass a value with the wrong type, you get an error at compile time, not run time.</p>

<p>Interfaces aren&rsquo;t restricted to static checking, though. You can check dynamically whether a particular interface value has an additional method. For example:</p>

<pre><code>type Stringer interface {
    String() string
}

func ToString(any interface{}) string {
    if v, ok := any.(Stringer); ok {
        return v.String()
    }
    switch v := any.(type) {
    case int:
        return strconv.Itoa(v)
    case float:
        return strconv.Ftoa(v, 'g', -1)
    }
    return &quot;???&quot;
}
</code></pre>

<p>The value any has static type interface{}, meaning no guarantee of any methods at all: it could contain any type. The “comma ok” assignment inside the if statement asks whether it is possible to convert any to an interface value of type Stringer, which has the method String. If so, the body of that statement calls the method to obtain a string to return. Otherwise, the switch picks off a few basic types before giving up. This is basically a stripped down version of what the <a href="http://golang.org/pkg/fmt/" target="_blank">fmt package</a> does. (The if could be replaced by adding case Stringer: at the top of the switch, but I used a separate statement to draw attention to the check.)</p>

<p>As a simple example, let&rsquo;s consider a 64-bit integer type with a String method that prints the value in binary and a trivial Get method:</p>

<pre><code>type Binary uint64

func (i Binary) String() string {
    return strconv.Uitob64(i.Get(), 2)
}

func (i Binary) Get() uint64 {
    return uint64(i)
}
</code></pre>

<p>A value of type Binary can be passed to ToString, which will format it using the String method, even though the program never says that Binary intends to implement Stringer. There&rsquo;s no need: the runtime can see that Binary has a String method, so it implements Stringer, even if the author of Binary has never heard of Stringer.</p>

<p>These examples show that even though all the implicit conversions are checked at compile time, explicit interface-to-interface conversions can inquire about method sets at run time. <a href="http://golang.org/doc/effective_go.html#interfaces" target="_blank">“Effective Go”</a> has more details about and examples of how interface values can be used.</p>

<p><strong>Interface Values</strong></p>

<p>Languages with methods typically fall into one of two camps: prepare tables for all the method calls statically (as in C++ and Java), or do a method lookup at each call (as in Smalltalk and its many imitators, JavaScript and Python included) and add fancy caching to make that call efficient. Go sits halfway between the two: it has method tables but computes them at run time. I don&rsquo;t know whether Go is the first language to use this technique, but it&rsquo;s certainly not a common one. (I&rsquo;d be interested to hear about earlier examples; leave a comment below.)</p>

<p>As a warmup, a value of type Binary is just a 64-bit integer made up of two 32-bit words (like in the <a href="http://research.swtch.com/2009/11/go-data-structures.html" target="_blank">last post</a>, we&rsquo;ll assume a 32-bit machine; this time memory grows down instead of to the right):</p>

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/go-data-structures-interfaces/gointer1.png" alt="Interfaces" title="gointer1" />
</p>

<p>Interface values are represented as a two-word pair giving a pointer to information about the type stored in the interface and a pointer to the associated data. Assigning b to an interface value of type Stringer sets both words of the interface value.</p>

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/go-data-structures-interfaces/gointer2.png" alt="Interfaces" title="gointer2" />
</p>

<p>(The pointers contained in the interface value are gray to emphasize that they are implicit, not directly exposed to Go programs.)</p>

<p>The first word in the interface value points at what I call an interface table or itable , pronounced i-table; in the <a href="http://golang.org/src/pkg/runtime/iface.c#L23" target="_blank">runtime sources<a/>, the C implementation name is Itab. The itable begins with some metadata about the types involved and then becomes a list of function pointers. Note that the itable corresponds to the interface type, not the dynamic type. In terms of our example, the itable for Stringer holding type Binary lists the methods used to satisfy Stringer, which is just String: Binary&rsquo;s other methods (Get) make no appearance in the itable.</p>

<p>The second word in the interface value points at the actual data, in this case a copy of b. The assignment var s Stringer = b makes a copy of b rather than point at b for the same reason that var c uint64 = b makes a copy: if b later changes, s and c are supposed to have the original value, not the new one. Values stored in interfaces might be arbitrarily large, but only one word is dedicated to holding the value in the interface structure, so the assignment allocates a chunk of memory on the heap and records the pointer in the one-word slot. (There&rsquo;s an obvious optimization when the value does fit in the slot; we&rsquo;ll get to that later.)</p>

<p>To check whether an interface value holds a particular type, as in the type switch above, the Go compiler generates code equivalent to the C expression s.tab-&gt;type to obtain the type pointer and check it against the desired type. If the types match, the value can be copied by by dereferencing &ldquo;s.data&rdquo;.</p>

<p>To call s.String(), the Go compiler generates code that does the equivalent of the C expression,
s.tab-&gt;fun[0](s.data) : it calls the appropriate function pointer from the itable, passing the interface value&rsquo;s data word as the function&rsquo;s first (in this example, only) argument. You can see this code if you run 8g -S x.go (details at the bottom of this post). Note that the function in the itable is being passed the 32-bit pointer from the second word of the interface value, not the 64-bit value it points at. In general, the interface call site doesn&rsquo;t know the meaning of this word nor how much data it points at. Instead, the interface code arranges that the function pointers in the itable expect the 32-bit representation stored in the interface values. Thus the function pointer in this example is (*Binary).String not Binary.String.</p>

<p>The example we&rsquo;re considering is an interface with just one method. An interface with more methods would have more entries in the fun list at the bottom of the itable.</p>

<p><strong>Computing the Itable</strong></p>

<p>Now we know what the itables look like, but where do they come from? Go&rsquo;s dynamic type conversions mean that it isn&rsquo;t reasonable for the compiler or linker to precompute all possible itables: there are too many (interface type, concrete type) pairs, and most won&rsquo;t be needed. Instead, the compiler generates a type description structure for each concrete type like Binary or int or func(map[int]string). Among other metadata, the type description structure contains a list of the methods implemented by that type. Similarly, the compiler generates a (different) type description structure for each interface type like Stringer; it too contains a method list. The interface runtime computes the itable by looking for each method listed in the interface type&rsquo;s method table in the concrete type&rsquo;s method table. The runtime caches the itable after generating it, so that this correspondence need only be computed once.</p>

<p>In our simple example, the method table for Stringer has one method, while the table for Binary has two methods. In general there might be ni methods for the interface type and nt methods for the concrete type. The obvious search to find the mapping from interface methods to concrete methods would take O(ni × nt) time, but we can do better. By sorting the two method tables and walking them simultaneously, we can build the mapping in O(ni + nt) time instead.</p>

<p><strong>Memory Optimizations</strong></p>

<p>The space used by the implementation described above can be optimized in two complementary ways.</p>

<p>First, if the interface type involved is empty—it has no methods—then the itable serves no purpose except to hold the pointer to the original type. In this case, the itable can be dropped and the value can point at the type directly:</p>

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/go-data-structures-interfaces/gointer3.png" alt="Interfaces" title="gointer3" />
</p>

<p>Whether an interface type has methods is a static property—either the type in the source code says interface{} or it says interace{ methods&hellip; }—so the compiler knows which representation is in use at each point in the program.</p>

<p>Second, if the value associated with the interface value can fit in a single machine word, there&rsquo;s no need to introduce the indirection or the heap allocation. If we define Binary32 to be like Binary but implemented as a uint32, it could be stored in an interface value by keeping the actual value in the second word:</p>

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/go-data-structures-interfaces/gointer4.png" alt="Interfaces" title="gointer4" />
</p>

<p>Whether the actual value is being pointed at or inlined depends on the size of the type. The compiler arranges for the functions listed in the type&rsquo;s method table (which get copied into the itables) to do the right thing with the word that gets passed in. If the receiver type fits in a word, it is used directly; if not, it is dereferenced. The diagrams show this: in the Binary version far above, the method in the itable is (*Binary).String, while in the Binary32 example, the method in the itable is Binary32.String not (*Binary32).String.</p>

<p>Of course, empty interfaces holding word-sized (or smaller) values can take advantage of both optimizations:</p>

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/blog/go-data-structures-interfaces/gointer5.png" alt="Interfaces" title="gointer5" />
</p>

<p><strong>Method Lookup Performance</strong></p>

<p>Smalltalk and the many dynamic systems that have followed it perform a method lookup every time a method gets called. For speed, many implementations use a simple one-entry cache at each call site, often in the instruction stream itself. In a multithreaded program, these caches must be managed carefully, since multiple threads could be at the same call site simultaneously. Even once the races have been avoided, the caches would end up being a source of memory contention.</p>

<p>Because Go has the hint of static typing to go along with the dynamic method lookups, it can move the lookups back from the call sites to the point when the value is stored in the interface. For example, consider this code snippet:</p>

<p>var any interface{}  // initialized elsewhere
   s := any.(Stringer)  // dynamic conversion
   for i := 0; i &lt; 100; i++ {
    fmt.Println(s.String())
   }</p>

<p>In Go, the itable gets computed (or found in a cache) during the assignment on line 2; the dispatch for the s.String() call executed on line 4 is a couple of memory fetches and a single indirect call instruction.</p>

<p>In contrast, the implementation of this program in a dynamic language like Smalltalk (or JavaScript, or Python, or &hellip;) would do the method lookup at line 4, which in a loop repeats needless work. The cache mentioned earlier makes this less expensive than it might be, but it&rsquo;s still more expensive than a single indirect call instruction.</p>

<p>Of course, this being a blog post, I don&rsquo;t have any numbers to back up this discussion, but it certainly seems like the lack of memory contention would be a big win in a heavily parallel program, as is being able to move the method lookup out of tight loops. Also, I&rsquo;m talking about the general architecture, not the specifics o the implementation: the latter probably has a few constant factor optimizations still available.</p>

<p><strong>More Information</strong></p>

<p>The interface runtime support is in <a href="http://code.google.com/p/go/source/browse/src/pkg/runtime/iface.c" target="_blank">$GOROOT/src/pkg/runtime/iface.c</a>. There&rsquo;s much more to say about interfaces (we haven&rsquo;t even seen an example of a pointer receiver yet) and the type descriptors (they power reflection in addition to the interface runtime) but those will have to wait for future posts.</p>

<p><strong>Code</strong></p>

<p>Supporting code (x.go):</p>

<pre><code>package main

import (
 &quot;fmt&quot;
 &quot;strconv&quot;
)

type Stringer interface {
 String() string
}

type Binary uint64

func (i Binary) String() string {
 return strconv.Uitob64(i.Get(), 2)
}

func (i Binary) Get() uint64 {
 return uint64(i)
}

func main() {
 b := Binary(200)
 s := Stringer(b)
 fmt.Println(s.String())
}
</code></pre>

<p>Selected output of 8g -S x.go:</p>

<pre><code>0045 (x.go:25) LEAL    s+-24(SP),BX
0046 (x.go:25) MOVL    4(BX),BP
0047 (x.go:25) MOVL    BP,(SP)
0048 (x.go:25) MOVL    (BX),BX
0049 (x.go:25) MOVL    20(BX),BX
0050 (x.go:25) CALL    ,BX
</code></pre>

<p>The LEAL loads the address of s into the register BX. (The notation n(SP) describes the word in memory at SP+n. 0(SP) can be shortened to (SP).) The next two MOVL instructions fetch the value from the second word in the interface and store it as the first function call argument, 0(SP). The final two MOVL instructions fetch the itable and then the function pointer from the itable, in preparation for calling that function.</p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
	  <entry>
	    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Can Civilization Survive Capitalism? this question made me start this blog.]]></title>
	    <link href="http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/03/05/chomsky-on-capitalism/"/>
	    <updated>2013-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	    <id>http://patrickToca.github.io//blog/english/2013/03/05/chomsky-on-capitalism/</id>
	    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.alternet.org/noam-chomsky-can-civilization-survive-capitalism/" target="_blank">original document</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="http://patrickToca.github.io//images/moebius/moebius-arzac-750.jpg" alt="Capitalism" title="Capitalism" />
</p>

<hr />

<h2>by Noam Chomsky - March 5, 2013</h2>

<p>The term &ldquo;capitalism&rdquo; is commonly used to refer to the U.S. economic system, with substantial state intervention ranging from subsidies for creative innovation to the &ldquo;too-big-to-fail&rdquo; government insurance policy for banks.</p>

<p>The system is highly monopolized, further limiting reliance on the market, and increasingly so: In the past 20 years the share of profits of the 200 largest enterprises has risen sharply, reports scholar Robert W. McChesney in his new book &ldquo;Digital Disconnect.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Capitalism&rdquo; is a term now commonly used to describe systems in which there are no capitalists: for example, the worker-owned Mondragon conglomerate in the Basque region of Spain, or the worker-owned enterprises expanding in northern Ohio, often with conservative support &ndash; both are discussed in important work by the scholar Gar Alperovitz.</p>

<p>Some might even use the term &ldquo;capitalism&rdquo; to refer to the industrial democracy advocated by John Dewey, America&rsquo;s leading social philosopher, in the late 19th century and early 20th century.</p>

<p>Dewey called for workers to be &ldquo;masters of their own industrial fate&rdquo; and for all institutions to be brought under public control, including the means of production, exchange, publicity, transportation and communication. Short of this, Dewey argued, politics will remain &ldquo;the shadow cast on society by big business.&rdquo;</p>

<p>The truncated democracy that Dewey condemned has been left in tatters in recent years. Now control of government is narrowly concentrated at the peak of the income scale, while the large majority &ldquo;down below&rdquo; has been virtually disenfranchised. The current political-economic system is a form of plutocracy, diverging sharply from democracy, if by that concept we mean political arrangements in which policy is significantly influenced by the public will.</p>

<p>There have been serious debates over the years about whether capitalism is compatible with democracy. If we keep to really existing capitalist democracy &ndash; RECD for short &ndash; the question is effectively answered: They are radically incompatible.</p>

<p>It seems to me unlikely that civilization can survive RECD and the sharply attenuated democracy that goes along with it. But could functioning democracy make a difference?</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s keep to the most critical immediate problem that civilization faces: environmental catastrophe. Policies and public attitudes diverge sharply, as is often the case under RECD. The nature of the gap is examined in several articles in the current issue of Daedalus, the journal of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.</p>

<p>Researcher Kelly Sims Gallagher finds that &ldquo;One hundred and nine countries have enacted some form of policy regarding renewable power, and 118 countries have set targets for renewable energy. In contrast, the United States has not adopted any consistent and stable set of policies at the national level to foster the use of renewable energy.&rdquo;</p>

<p>It is not public opinion that drives American policy off the international spectrum. Quite the opposite. Opinion is much closer to the global norm than the U.S. government&rsquo;s policies reflect, and much more supportive of actions needed to confront the likely environmental disaster predicted by an overwhelming scientific consensus &ndash; and one that&rsquo;s not too far off; affecting the lives of our grandchildren, very likely.</p>

<p>As Jon A. Krosnick and Bo MacInnis report in Daedalus: &ldquo;Huge majorities have favored steps by the federal government to reduce the amount of greenhouse gas emissions generated when utilities produce electricity. In 2006, 86 percent of respondents favored requiring utilities, or encouraging them with tax breaks, to reduce the amount of greenhouse gases they emit. Also in that year, 87 percent favored tax breaks for utilities that produce more electricity from water, wind or sunlight [ These majorities were maintained between 2006 and 2010 and shrank somewhat after that.</p>

<p>The fact that the public is influenced by science is deeply troubling to those who dominate the economy and state policy.</p>

<p>One current illustration of their concern is the &ldquo;Environmental Literacy Improvement Act&rdquo; proposed to state legislatures by ALEC, the American Legislative Exchange Council, a corporate-funded lobby that designs legislation to serve the needs of the corporate sector and extreme wealth.</p>

<p>The ALEC Act mandates &ldquo;balanced teaching&rdquo; of climate science in K-12 classrooms. &ldquo;Balanced teaching&rdquo; is a code phrase that refers to teaching climate-change denial, to &ldquo;balance&rdquo; mainstream climate science. It is analogous to the &ldquo;balanced teaching&rdquo; advocated by creationists to enable the teaching of &ldquo;creation science&rdquo; in public schools. Legislation based on ALEC models has already been introduced in several states.</p>

<p>Of course, all of this is dressed up in rhetoric about teaching critical thinking &ndash; a fine idea, no doubt, but it&rsquo;s easy to think up far better examples than an issue that threatens our survival and has been selected because of its importance in terms of corporate profits.</p>

<p>Media reports commonly present a controversy between two sides on climate change.</p>

<p>One side consists of the overwhelming majority of scientists, the world&rsquo;s major national academies of science, the professional science journals and the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change.</p>

<p>They agree that global warming is taking place, that there is a substantial human component, that the situation is serious and perhaps dire, and that very soon, maybe within decades, the world might reach a tipping point where the process will escalate sharply and will be irreversible, with severe social and economic effects. It is rare to find such consensus on complex scientific issues.</p>

<p>The other side consists of skeptics, including a few respected scientists who caution that much is unknown &ndash; which means that things might not be as bad as thought, or they might be worse.</p>

<p>Omitted from the contrived debate is a much larger group of skeptics: highly regarded climate scientists who see the IPCC&rsquo;s regular reports as much too conservative. And these scientists have repeatedly been proven correct, unfortunately.</p>

<p>The propaganda campaign has apparently had some effect on U.S. public opinion, which is more skeptical than the global norm. But the effect is not significant enough to satisfy the masters. That is presumably why sectors of the corporate world are launching their attack on the educational system, in an effort to counter the public&rsquo;s dangerous tendency to pay attention to the conclusions of scientific research.</p>

<p>At the Republican National Committee&rsquo;s Winter Meeting a few weeks ago, Louisiana Gov. Bobby Jindal warned the leadership that &ldquo;We must stop being the stupid party &hellip; We must stop insulting the intelligence of voters.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Within the RECD system it is of extreme importance that we become the stupid nation, not misled by science and rationality, in the interests of the short-term gains of the masters of the economy and political system, and damn the consequences.</p>

<p>These commitments are deeply rooted in the fundamentalist market doctrines that are preached within RECD, though observed in a highly selective manner, so as to sustain a powerful state that serves wealth and power.</p>

<p>The official doctrines suffer from a number of familiar &ldquo;market inefficiencies,&rdquo; among them the failure to take into account the effects on others in market transactions. The consequences of these &ldquo;externalities&rdquo; can be substantial. The current financial crisis is an illustration. It is partly traceable to the major banks and investment firms&rsquo; ignoring &ldquo;systemic risk&rdquo; &ndash; the possibility that the whole system would collapse &ndash; when they undertook risky transactions.</p>

<p>Environmental catastrophe is far more serious: The externality that is being ignored is the fate of the species. And there is nowhere to run, cap in hand, for a bailout.</p>

<p>In future, historians (if there are any) will look back on this curious spectacle taking shape in the early 21st century. For the first time in human history, humans are facing the significant prospect of severe calamity as a result of their actions &ndash; actions that are battering our prospects of decent survival.</p>

<p>Those historians will observe that the richest and most powerful country in history, which enjoys incomparable advantages, is leading the effort to intensify the likely disaster. Leading the effort to preserve conditions in which our immediate descendants might have a decent life are the so-called &ldquo;primitive&rdquo; societies: First Nations, tribal, indigenous, aboriginal.</p>

<p>The countries with large and influential indigenous populations are well in the lead in seeking to preserve the planet. The countries that have driven indigenous populations to extinction or extreme marginalization are racing toward destruction.</p>

<p>Thus Ecuador, with its large indigenous population, is seeking aid from the rich countries to allow it to keep its substantial oil reserves underground, where they should be.</p>

<p>Meanwhile the U.S. and Canada are seeking to burn fossil fuels, including the extremely dangerous Canadian tar sands, and to do so as quickly and fully as possible, while they hail the wonders of a century of (largely meaningless) energy independence without a side glance at what the world might look like after this extravagant commitment to self-destruction.</p>

<p>This observation generalizes: Throughout the world, indigenous societies are struggling to protect what they sometimes call &ldquo;the rights of nature,&rdquo; while the civilized and sophisticated scoff at this silliness.</p>

<p>This is all exactly the opposite of what rationality would predict &ndash; unless it is the skewed form of reason that passes through the filter of RECD.</p>
<hr/><a href="http://patrickToca.github.io//english/about/">Disclaimer</a>]]></content>
	  </entry>
  	
  
	
  

</feed>
